[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "1.\t Choose the correct statement regarding superkeys",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tA superkey is an attribute or a group of multiple attributes that can uniquely identify a tuple",
            "b)\tA superkey is a tuple or a set of multiple tuples that can uniquely identify an attribute",
            "c)\tEvery superkey is a candidate key",
            "d)\tA superkey is an attribute or a set of attributes that distinguish the relation from other relations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A superkey is an attribute or a set of multiple attributes that can uniquely identify a tuple. It is used to differentiate between tuples."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "What is an Instance of a Database?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe logical design of the database system",
            "b)\tThe entire set of attributes of the Database put together in a single relation",
            "c)\tThe state of the database system at any given point of time",
            "d)\tThe initial values inserted into the Database immediately after its creation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The state of the database system at any given point of time is called as an Instance of the database."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "What is a foreign key?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tA foreign key is a primary key of a relation which is an attribute in another relation",
            "b)\tA foreign key is a superkey of a relation which is an attribute in more than one other relations",
            "c)\tA foreign key is an attribute of a relation that is a primary key of another relation",
            "d)\tA foreign key is the primary key of a relation that does not occur anywhere else in the schema"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A foreign key is an attribute of a relation that is initially a primary key of another relation. A foreign key usage preserves referential integrity."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "What action does  ⋈  operator perform in relational algebra",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOutput specified attributes from all rows of the input relation and remove duplicate tuples from the output",
            "b)\tOutputs pairs of rows from the two input relations that have the same value on all attributes that have the same name",
            "c)\tOutput all pairs of rows from the two input relations (regardless of whether or not they have the same values on common attributes)",
            "d)\tReturn rows of the input relation that satisfy the predicate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ⋈ Outputs specified attributes from all rows of the input relation. Remove duplicate tuples from the output. The operation is called the join operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "What does the “x” operator do in relational algebra?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOutput specified attributes from all rows of the input relation. Remove duplicate tuples from the output",
            "b)\tOutput pairs of rows from the two input relations that have the same value on all attributes that have the same name",
            "c)\tOutput all pairs of rows from the two input relations (regardless of whether or not they have the same values on common attributes)",
            "d)\tReturns the rows of the input relation that satisfy the predicate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The “x” operator outputs all pairs of rows from the two input relations (regardless of whether or not they have the same values on common attributes). This operation is called as the Cartesian product operation and is similar to the Cartesian product of sets."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "An attribute is a __________ in a relation.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRow",
            "b)\tColumn",
            "c)\tValue",
            "d)\tTuple"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An attribute is a column in a relation. A tuple is a row in a relation."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "What is the method of specifying a primary key in a schema description?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBy writing it in bold letters",
            "b)\tBy underlining it using a dashed line",
            "c)\tBy writing it in capital letters",
            "d)\tBy underlining it using a bold line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We can specify a primary key in schema description by underlining the respective attribute with a bold line."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Which of the following information does an SQL DDL not specify?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe schema for each relation",
            "b)\tThe integrity constraints",
            "c)\tThe operations on the tuples",
            "d)\tThe security and authorization information for each relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The SQL DDL does not specify the operations that are supposed to be made on the tuples. DDL means Data definition language, hence it does not include the operations made."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Which of the following data types does the SQL standard not support?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tchar(n)",
            "b)\tString(n)",
            "c)\tvarchar(n)",
            "d)\tfloat(n)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The SQL standard does not support String(n) but it supports char, varchar and float."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Which command is used to create a new relation in SQL",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tcreate table( ,   …)",
            "b)\tcreate relation( ,   …)",
            "c)\tnew table( ,   …)",
            "d)\tnew relation(  ,   …)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We use the create table command to create a new relation in the database. The syntax is\n\t\tcreate table( ,   …);"
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "If a1, a2, a3 are attributes in a relation and S is another relation, which of the following is an incorrect specification of an integrity constraint?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tprimary key(a1, a2, a3)",
            "b)\tprimary key(a1)",
            "c)\tforeign key(a1, a2) references S",
            "d)\tforeign key(a1, a2)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Whenever the integrity constraint foreign key is mentioned, the attributes that are the foreign keys should always be referenced from the relation in which they are primary keys."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "What is the syntax to load data into the database? (Consider D as the database and a, b, c as data)",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tenter into D (a, b, c);",
            "b)\tinsert into D values (a, b, c);",
            "c)\tinsert into D (a, b, c);",
            "d)\tinsert (a, b, c) values into D;"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To load data into a database we use the insert into command. The syntax is\n\t         insert into D values (a, b, c) where a, b, c are the appropriate values"
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": " Which of the following commands do we use to delete a relation (R) from a database?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tdrop table R",
            "b)\tdrop relation R",
            "c)\tdelete table R",
            "d)\tdelete from R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The drop table command is used to delete a relation from a database whereas the delete table removes all the tuples from a relation"
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "Which of the following commands do we use to delete all the tuples from a relation (R)?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tdelete table R",
            "b)\tdrop table R",
            "c)\tdelete from R",
            "d)\tdrop from R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The delete from command is used to delete all the tuples in a relation. The drop table totally deletes a relation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "Choose the correct command to delete an attribute A from a relation R",
        "Options": [
            "a)\talter table R delete A",
            "b)\talter table R drop A",
            "c)\talter table drop A from R",
            "d)\tdelete A from R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We can delete an attribute from a relation using the alter table command with the following syntax\nalter table  drop "
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "What does the notnull integrity constraint do?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt ensures that at least one tuple is present in the relation",
            "b)\tIt ensures that at least one foreign key is present in the relation",
            "c)\tIt ensures that all tuples have a finite value on a specified attribute",
            "d)\tIt ensures that all tuples have finite attributes on all the relations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It creates a relation apartment with three attributes as specified. The attribute ownername cannot be null because it is the primary key of the relation."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following syntax of the basic query is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tselect <relation> from <attribute>",
            "b)\tselect <attribute> from <elation>",
            "c)\tselect <tuple> from <relation>",
            "d)\tselect <tuple> from <attribute>"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The select clause is used to select a specific attribute from a given relation. So, the syntactically correct statement is select <attribute> from <relation>."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "2.\tWhich of the following keywords is used beside the select clause to explicitly specify that duplicates are not removed?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tall",
            "b)\tnot unique",
            "c)\tnotnull",
            "d)\tinclude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The “all” keyword is used beside the select clause to explicitly specify that duplicates are not removed."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich of the following logical connectives is not included in SQL?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tand",
            "b)\tor",
            "c)\tnor",
            "d)\tnot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: “not” is not a logical connective included in the SQL. The and, or and nor are logical connectives that are included in SQL. "
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "4.\tThe where clause is a predicate involving attributes of the relation in the ______ clause.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tselect",
            "b)\tfrom",
            "c)\twith",
            "d)\tnone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The “from” clause contains the attribute names on which the “which” clause can be used on. "
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "What does the above query do?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt gives all the tuples having a distinct dept_name",
            "b)\tIt gives the dept_name attribute values of all tuples without repetition",
            "c)\tIt gives all the dept_name attribute of all the tuples",
            "d)\tIt gives all the tuples having a null value under the dept_name attribute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The distinct keyword is used to explicitly force the elimination of duplicate tuples. Thus, the above query excludes duplicates. "
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "7.\tThe ________ clause is used to list the attributes desired in the result of a query",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tselect",
            "b)\tfrom",
            "c)\twhere",
            "d)\tcreate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: student.branch = department.branch verifies whether both the values of the attributes are same in both the relations and returns the value. "
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "8.\tIf we specify multiple relations in the from clause and do not specify any conditions in the where clause, what will the result be?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe natural join of both the relations",
            "b)\tThe left outer join of both the relations",
            "c)\tA syntactical error",
            "d)\tThe Cartesian product of both the relations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The select clause is used to list the attributes desired in the result of a query."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "10.\tWhat does the natural join operation do?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt considers only those pairs of tuples that have the same value on those attributes that appear in the schemas of both relations",
            "b)\tIt considers only those pairs of tuples that have the same value on at least one of the attributes that appear in the schemas of both the relations",
            "c)\tIt considers only those pairs of tuples that do not have the same value on those attributes that appear in the schemas of both relations",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If we specify multiple relations in the from clause and do not specify any conditions in the where clause, the default definition given by the from clause is the Cartesian product of the relations listed in the clause. So it returns all the possible combinations of the tuples of the two relations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Which keyword is used to rename a relation in a query?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\trename",
            "b)\tas",
            "c)\tis",
            "d)\tto"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Multiple conditions in the where clause are separated by the “and” keyword. "
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "13.\tWhile operating with strings, what does “_ _ _%” match with?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tA string of three letters",
            "b)\tA string of at least three letters",
            "c)\tA string of three words",
            "d)\tA string of at least three words"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The natural join operation considers only those pairs of tuples that have the same value on those attributes that appear in the schemas of both the relations. The natural join operation operates on 2 relations and gives a relation as the result. "
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "1.\tWhat is the function of the union operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt combines the results of any two different queries",
            "b)\tIt combines the results of two different queries which have the same set of attributes in the select clause",
            "c)\tIt combines the results of two different queries which have the same condition in the where clause",
            "d)\tIt gives the Cartesian product of the results of any 2 queries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The union operation combines the results of two different queries which have the same set of attributes in the select clause. It automatically eliminates duplicates. "
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "2.\tWhat is the function of the intersect operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt returns the intersection of the results of the results of any two different queries",
            "b)\tIt returns the intersection of the results of two different queries which have the same set of attributes in the select clause",
            "c)\tIt returns the intersection of the results of two different queries which have the same condition in the where clause",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The intersect operation returns the intersection of the results of the results of two different queries which have the same set of attributes in the select clause. It automatically eliminates duplicates. "
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "3.\tWhat is the function of the except operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt excludes all the results present in both the queries",
            "b)\tIt includes the results of the second query but excludes the results of the first query",
            "c)\tIt includes the results of the first query but excludes the results of the second query",
            "d)\tIt includes all the results of both queries but removes duplicates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The except operation includes the results of the first query but excludes the results of the second query. It automatically eliminates duplicates but if we want to retain duplicates we must use except all in place of except. "
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "4.\tWhen does the predicate is null succeed?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIf the value on which it is applied is finite",
            "b)\tIf the value on which it is applied is invalid",
            "c)\tIf the value on which it is applied is blank",
            "d)\tIf the value on which it is applied is more than the allowed limit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The is null predicate succeeds when the value on which it is applied is blank/null. "
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "5.\tUsing the _______ clause retains only one copy of identical tuples",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tdistinct",
            "b)\tis not null",
            "c)\tno repeat",
            "d)\tfrom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Specifying the distinct clause beside the select clause retains only one copy of identical tuples resulting from the query. "
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "6.\tObserve the following query and choose the correct option<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"sql\"><pre class=\"de1\"><span class=\"kw1\">SELECT</span> <span class=\"kw1\">DISTINCT</span> name \n<span class=\"kw1\">FROM</span> student\n<span class=\"kw1\">WHERE</span> ID <span class=\"kw1\">IS</span> <span class=\"kw1\">NOT</span> <span class=\"kw1\">NULL</span>;</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe query is syntactically wrong",
            "b)\tThe query gives all the possible student names where a finite value exists for ID",
            "c)\tThe query gives the names of the students that have a null ID and it also excludes identical names",
            "d)\tThe query gives the student names where a finite value exists for ID and it excludes identical names"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The distinct keyword is used to remove tuples that have identical values. The is not null clause checks only for ID’s that are not null values. "
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "7.\tWhat will be the result of the following query?<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"sql\"><pre class=\"de1\"><span class=\"br0\">(</span><span class=\"kw1\">SELECT</span> studentid\n<span class=\"kw1\">FROM</span> student \n<span class=\"kw1\">WHERE</span> <span class=\"kw1\">SECTION</span> <span class=\"sy0\">=</span> <span class=\"st0\">'c'</span><span class=\"br0\">)</span>\n<span class=\"kw1\">EXCEPT</span>\n<span class=\"br0\">(</span><span class=\"kw1\">SELECT</span> studentid\n<span class=\"kw1\">FROM</span> student\n<span class=\"kw1\">WHERE</span> roll &amp;lt;<span class=\"nu0\">10</span><span class=\"br0\">)</span>;</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAll the values of the studentid for which section is c and roll < 10",
            "b)\tAll the values of the studentid for which section is c and roll > 10",
            "c)\tAll the values of the studentid for which section not c and roll < 10",
            "d)\tAll the values of the studentid for which section not c and roll > 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The except operation excludes all the tuples that are present in the result of the second query from the result of the first query. It also excludes all duplicates from the relation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following correctly describes the between predicate in the where clause?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt is used to check whether a value is in between two specified values",
            "b)\tIt is used to check whether a value is exactly in the center of the relation alphabetically",
            "c)\tIt is used to check whether a value is in between any two other values in the database",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The between predicate in the where clause is used to check whether a value is in between two externally specified values. This clause is used to list out all tuples having a value within a range. "
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following is not a built in aggregate function in SQL?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tavg",
            "b)\tmax",
            "c)\ttotal",
            "d)\tcount"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: SQL does not include total as a built in aggregate function. The avg is used to find average, max is used to find the maximum and the count is used to count the number of values. "
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "2.\tObserve the given SQL query and choose the correct option.<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"sql\"><pre class=\"de1\"><span class=\"kw1\">SELECT</span> branch_name<span class=\"sy0\">,</span> <span class=\"kw1\">COUNT</span> <span class=\"br0\">(</span><span class=\"kw1\">DISTINCT</span> customer_name<span class=\"br0\">)</span> \n<span class=\"kw1\">FROM</span> depositor<span class=\"sy0\">,</span> account \n<span class=\"kw1\">WHERE</span> depositor<span class=\"sy0\">.</span>account_number <span class=\"sy0\">=</span> account<span class=\"sy0\">.</span>account_number \n<span class=\"kw1\">GROUP</span> <span class=\"kw1\">BY</span> branch_id</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe query is syntactically correct but gives the wrong answer",
            "b)\tThe query is syntactically wrong",
            "c)\tThe query is syntactically correct and gives the correct answer",
            "d)\tThe query contains one or more wrongly named clauses."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The query is syntactically wrong. The attribute in the group by clause must be one of the attributes specified in the select clause. "
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "4.\tWe apply the aggregate function to a group of sets of tuples using the _______ clause.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tgroup by",
            "b)\tgroup",
            "c)\tgroup set",
            "d)\tgroup attribute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SQL does not permit distinct with count(*) but the use of distinct is allowed with max and min. "
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "5.\tChoose the correct option regarding the query<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"sql\"><pre class=\"de1\"><span class=\"kw1\">SELECT</span> branch_name<span class=\"sy0\">,</span> <span class=\"kw1\">COUNT</span> <span class=\"br0\">(</span><span class=\"kw1\">DISTINCT</span> customer_name<span class=\"br0\">)</span> \n<span class=\"kw1\">FROM</span> depositor<span class=\"sy0\">,</span> account \n<span class=\"kw1\">WHERE</span> depositor<span class=\"sy0\">.</span>account_number <span class=\"sy0\">=</span> account<span class=\"sy0\">.</span>account_number \n       <span class=\"kw1\">GROUP</span> <span class=\"kw1\">BY</span> branch_id\n       <span class=\"kw1\">HAVING</span> avg<span class=\"br0\">(</span>balance<span class=\"br0\">)</span> <span class=\"sy0\">=</span> <span class=\"nu0\">10000</span>;</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe having clause checks whether the query result is true or not",
            "b)\tThe having clause does not check for any condition",
            "c)\tThe having clause allows only those tuples that have average balance 10000",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We apply the aggregate function to a group of sets of tuples using the group by clause. The group by clause must always be used whenever we are willing to apply the aggregate function to a group of sets of tuples. "
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "6.\tThe _____ aggregation operation adds up all the values of the attribute",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tadd",
            "b)\tavg",
            "c)\tmax",
            "d)\tsum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The having clause is used to check for conditions that need to be set on aggregate functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich keyword is used to rename the resulting attribute after the application of the aggregation function?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\trename",
            "b)\tas",
            "c)\treplace",
            "d)\tto"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The sum aggregation operation adds up all the values of the specified attribute. There does not exist any aggregation such as add."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "10.\tWhat values does the count(*) function ignore?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRepetitive values",
            "b)\tNull values",
            "c)\tCharacters",
            "d)\tIntegers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Any attribute which is present in the having clause without being aggregated must be present in the group by clause. Otherwise, the query is considered to be erroneous."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "1.\tWhat is a subquery?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tA subquery is a select-from-where expression that is nested within another query",
            "b)\tA subquery is any query that is nested within another query",
            "c)\tA subquery is a relation that is externally specified which can be used to handle data in queries",
            "d)\tA subquery is a condition that excludes all the invalid tuples from the database"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A subquery is a select-from-where expression that is nested within another query. Common uses for sub-queries are to perform tests for set membership, make set comparisons etc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "2.\tIf a set is a collection of values given by the select clause, The ______ connective tests for set membership",
        "Options": [
            "a)\twithin",
            "b)\tinclude",
            "c)\tunder",
            "d)\tin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The in connective is used to test for the membership in a set, where the set is a collection of values given by the select clause."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "4.\tWhat is the result of the following query?<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"sql\"><pre class=\"de1\"><span class=\"kw1\">SELECT</span> studname\n<span class=\"kw1\">FROM</span> college\n<span class=\"kw1\">WHERE</span> marks &amp;gt; <span class=\"kw1\">SOME</span> <span class=\"br0\">(</span><span class=\"kw1\">SELECT</span> marks\n                                        <span class=\"kw1\">FROM</span> student\n               \t\t    <span class=\"kw1\">WHERE</span> <span class=\"kw1\">SECTION</span> <span class=\"sy0\">=</span> <span class=\"st0\">'c'</span><span class=\"br0\">)</span>;</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe query gives all the studnames for which marks are greater than all the students in section c",
            "b)\tThe query gives all the studnames for which the marks are greater than at least on student in section c",
            "c)\tThe query gives all the studnames for which the marks are less than all the students in section c",
            "d)\tThe query is syntactically incorrect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nested Subqueries can be used for comparing two different sets. Set comparison is an important function of the nested sub-queries. "
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "5.\t The ________ comparison checker is used to check “each and every” condition",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tall",
            "b)\tand",
            "c)\tevery",
            "d)\teach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The “some” comparison is used to check for at least one condition. The > symbol is used to test whether the marks are greater than the right hand side or not. "
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "6.\tThe ______ construct returns true if a given tuple is present in the subquery.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tnot exists",
            "b)\tpresent",
            "c)\tnot present",
            "d)\texists"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The all comparison checker is used to check “each and every” condition. The “each” and “every” comparison checkers do not exist in SQL. "
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "7.\tWhat is a correlated sub-query?",
        "Options": [
            "a) An independent query that uses the correlation name of another independent query.",
            "b) A sub-query that uses the correlation name of an outer query",
            "c) A sub-query that substitutes the names of the outer query",
            "d) A sub-query that does not depend on its outer query’s correlation names"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The exists construct returns true if a given tuple is present in the subquery. The not exists construct gives true if a given tuple is not present in the subquery."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "8.\tThe _________ construct returns true if the argument in the sub-query is void of duplicates",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tnot null",
            "b)\tnot unique",
            "c)\tunique",
            "d)\tnull"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A correlated sub-query is the one that uses the correlation name of an outer query. "
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "10.\tChoose the correct option regarding the following query<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"sql\"><pre class=\"de1\"><span class=\"kw1\">WITH</span> max_marks <span class=\"br0\">(</span><span class=\"kw1\">VALUE</span><span class=\"br0\">)</span> <span class=\"kw1\">AS</span>\n<span class=\"br0\">(</span><span class=\"kw1\">SELECT</span> <span class=\"kw1\">MAX</span><span class=\"br0\">(</span>marks<span class=\"br0\">)</span>\n<span class=\"kw1\">FROM</span> student<span class=\"br0\">)</span>\n<span class=\"kw1\">SELECT</span> studentID\n<span class=\"kw1\">FROM</span> student<span class=\"sy0\">,</span>max_marks\n<span class=\"kw1\">WHERE</span> student<span class=\"sy0\">.</span>marks <span class=\"sy0\">=</span> max_marks<span class=\"sy0\">.</span>value;</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe query is syntactically wrong",
            "b)\tThe query gives the studentID of the student with the maximum marks",
            "c)\tThe query gives the maximum marks amongst all the students",
            "d)\tThe query gives all the studentID values except the student with the maximum marks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: unique\nExplanation: The unique construct returns true if the argument in the sub-query is void of duplicates. The not null construct avoids the specification of null values into the attribute. "
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "11.\tSQL subqueries that can occur wherever a value is permitted provided the subquery gives only one tuple with a single attribute are called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tExact Subqueries",
            "b)\tVector Subqueries",
            "c)\tPositive Subqueries",
            "d)\tScalar Subqueries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SQL allows the use of Subqueries inside the from clause. The subquery used in the from clause must have in its result the attributes that are specified in the select clause."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "2.\tHow many relations can a delete command operate on?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t0",
            "b)\t1",
            "c)\t2",
            "d)\tInfinitely many"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: the from key word is specified beside delete clause to indicate the relation from which the tuple needs to be deleted. "
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "3.\t What is the result of the following query?<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"sql\"><pre class=\"de1\"><span class=\"kw1\">DELETE</span> <span class=\"kw1\">FROM</span> student\n<span class=\"kw1\">WHERE</span> marks &amp;lt; <span class=\"br0\">(</span><span class=\"kw1\">SELECT</span> avg<span class=\"br0\">(</span>marks<span class=\"br0\">)</span>\n                             <span class=\"kw1\">FROM</span> student<span class=\"br0\">)</span>;</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe query deletes all the tuples whose marks are greater than the average marks",
            "b)\tThe query deletes all the tuples whose marks are less than the average marks",
            "c)\tThe query deletes all the values under the marks attribute which are less than the average",
            "d)\tThe query is syntactically wrong and does not execute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The delete command can operate only on one relation. You cannot give commands like delete R1, R2. "
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "4.\tWhat is the format of entering date into a database while inserting data into it?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tYYYY-MM-DD",
            "b)\t“YYYY-MM-DD”",
            "c)\t‘YYYY-MM-DD’",
            "d)\t“DD-MM-YYYY”"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The query deletes all the tuples from the student relation as per the condition specified in the where clause i.e. wherever the marks are less than average marks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "5.\tChoose the correct option regarding the following query<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"sql\"><pre class=\"de1\"><span class=\"kw1\">INSERT</span> <span class=\"kw1\">INTO</span> course <span class=\"br0\">(</span><span class=\"st0\">'CS-67'</span> <span class=\"sy0\">,</span> <span class=\"st0\">'course name'</span><span class=\"sy0\">,</span> <span class=\"st0\">'any'</span> <span class=\"sy0\">,</span> <span class=\"nu0\">5</span><span class=\"br0\">)</span>;</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tData is inserted into the course relation",
            "b)\tData is not inserted into the course relation due to incorrect specification",
            "c)\tData is inserted into the CS-67 relation",
            "d)\tData is not inserted due to the incorrect use of syntax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct format for entering date into the database while inserting data is\n‘YYYY-MM-DD’."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "6.\tTo change a value in a tuple without changing all the values in the tuple, we use the _____ statement",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tinsert",
            "b)\tinsert some",
            "c)\tupdate",
            "d)\talter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Data is not inserted because, the proper syntax is\ninsert into <relation name> values (<data>);"
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "7.\tWhat does the following query do?<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"sql\"><pre class=\"de1\"><span class=\"kw1\">UPDATE</span> student \n<span class=\"kw1\">SET</span> marks <span class=\"sy0\">=</span> marks<span class=\"sy0\">*</span><span class=\"nu0\">1.10</span>;</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt increases the marks of all the students by 10%",
            "b)\tIt decreases the marks of all the students by 90%",
            "c)\tIt increases the marks of all the students by 110%",
            "d)\tIt is syntactically wrong"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To change a value in a tuple without changing the entire values in the tuple, we use the update statement. Eg: update employee set salary = salary*1.5; "
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "9.\tScalar Subqueries can be used in the SQL update statement when they are used under the ____ clause",
        "Options": [
            "a)\twhere",
            "b)\twith",
            "c)\tset",
            "d)\tend"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The update clause is used to edit a specific value in the tuple. The set command is used to set the value of an attribute in a tuple."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich of the following cannot be used to modify the data in a database",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tupdate",
            "b)\tinsert",
            "c)\tdelete",
            "d)\tdrop"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Writing a where clause under the update statement enables us to specify a condition for the selection of tuples whose values need to be updated. "
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "1.\tThe on condition appears at the _______ of the join expression",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBeginning",
            "b)\tEnd",
            "c)\tBetween",
            "d)\tThe on condition is not related to join expression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The on condition appears at the end of the join expression. Because it states the condition that the relations under the join operations get matched based on. "
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "2.\tWhat is the difference between a join and an outer join operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThere is no difference",
            "b)\tJoin preserves a few tuples that are otherwise lost in the outer join",
            "c)\tOuter join preserves a few tuples that are otherwise lost in the join",
            "d)\tAn outer join can be used only on outer queries whereas a join operation can be used in Subqueries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The outer join operation preserves a few tuples that are otherwise lost in the join operation. The outer join operation preserves the tuples to the right of the operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "3.\tThe join operations that do not retain mismatched tuples are called as _________ operations",
        "Options": [
            "a)\touter join",
            "b)\tnatural join",
            "c)\tfull outer join",
            "d)\tinner join"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The join operations that do not retain mismatched tuples are called as inner join operations. The inner join operations do not preserve any tuples that are otherwise preserved in the outer join operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "4.\tWhat is the function of a left outer join?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt preserves tuples only in the relation named before the operation",
            "b)\tIt preserves tuples only in the relation named after the operation",
            "c)\tIt preserved tuples in the relations named on both the sides of the operation",
            "d)\tIt does not preserve any tuples on either side of the relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The left outer join operation preserves the tuples named before the operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "5.\tWhat is the function of a full outer join?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt preserves tuples only in the relation named before the operation",
            "b)\tIt preserves tuples only in the relation named after the operation",
            "c)\tIt preserved tuples in the relations named on both the sides of the operation",
            "d)\tIt does not preserve any tuples on either side of the relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The full outer join operation preserves the tuples named on both the sides of the operation. Unlike the inner join, outer joins preserve tuples from either or both sides of the operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "6.\tWhat is the function of a right outer join?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt preserves tuples only in the relation named before the operation",
            "b)\tIt preserves tuples only in the relation named after the operation",
            "c)\tIt preserved tuples in the relations named on both the sides of the operation",
            "d)\tIt does not preserve any tuples on either side of the relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The right outer join operation preserves the tuples named after the operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "7.\tWhat is the function of inner join?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt preserves tuples only in the relation named before the operation",
            "b)\tIt preserves tuples only in the relation named after the operation",
            "c)\tIt preserved tuples in the relations named on both the sides of the operation",
            "d)\tIt does not preserve any tuples on either side of the relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The join operations that do not retain mismatched tuples are called as inner join operations. The inner join operation does not preserve any tuples on either side of the relation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich off the following is not a valid type of join?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tleft outer join",
            "b)\touter join",
            "c)\tjoin",
            "d)\tfull join"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The on condition is a part of the outer join syntax but the where clause isn’t. "
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "10.\tIf a left outer join is performed and the tuple on the left hand side does not match with the tuple on the right hand side, what happens to the values that are preserved on the left hand side?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThey are given null values",
            "b)\tThey are given a random value",
            "c)\tThe user is asked to enter data",
            "d)\tThe query is declared invalid by the compiler"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There is no such join called as full join. There is a full outer join but a full join does not exist. "
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "1.\tWhat is a view?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAn brief description of the schema diagram.",
            "b)\tA relation that is not a part of the schema but is a virtual relation",
            "c)\tAny relation that is a part of the schema",
            "d)\tA relation that is a part of the schema but which needs to be specified in every operation made on that particular relation."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A relation that is not a part of the schema but is a virtual relation is called as view. Views improve writability as viewing the entire logical model is not feasible. "
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "2.\tWhat is the command used to define view in SQL?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tdefine view",
            "b)\tnew view",
            "c)\tcreate view",
            "d)\tnone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We use the create view command to define a view in SQL. "
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "What is the result of the above query?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt creates a view named studentdet with 3 attributes",
            "b)\tIt creates a view named studentdet with 1 attribute",
            "c)\tIt creates a view named ID with 2 attributes",
            "d)\tIt is syntactically wrong and does not give a result"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: immediately after specifying the name of the view, we have to write the “as” keyword. So this query does not give any result as it is syntactically incorrect. "
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "5.\tIf the actual relations used in the view definition change, the view is updated immediately. Such views are called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInstant views",
            "b)\tInstantaneous views",
            "c)\tMaterialistic views",
            "d)\tMaterialized views"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One view can be used to define another view in its expression. This further improves the writability of the code as we are reducing the entire logical model. "
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "6.\tThe process of maintaining views up to date is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tView maintenance",
            "b)\tView updating",
            "c)\tView materialization",
            "d)\tView isolation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the actual relations used in the view definition change, the view is updated immediately. Such views are called Materialized views. Materialized views help to keep the database up-to-date. "
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "7.\tHow can we insert data into a view?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tinsert into  ();",
            "b)\tcreate data  values ();",
            "c)\tenter  ();",
            "d)\tinsert into  values ();"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The process of maintaining views up to date is called View maintenance. View maintenance can be done immediately when any of the views is updated. "
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "9.\tThe _______ statement makes the updates performed by the transaction permanent.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFinalize work",
            "b)\tFinish work",
            "c)\tCommit work",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We can insert data into a view using the inset into values (); statement. This operation can be done only if the view is updatable. "
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "10.\tThe _______ statement causes the statements to undo all the updates performed on the transaction",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUndo work",
            "b)\tRollback work",
            "c)\tCommit work",
            "d)\tReplace work"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We can update a view only if it has a single database relation in the “from” clause."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following is not an integrity constraint?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tnot null",
            "b)\tunique",
            "c)\tidentical",
            "d)\tcheck"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Identical is not an allowed integrity constraint in SQL. Not null prevents null values and unique only allows unique values to be entered. Check checks for a given condition. "
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "2.\tWhat is the function of the not null constraint?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt prevents illegal data from being entered into the database",
            "b)\tIt ensures that data is entered into the database",
            "c)\tIt ensures that the data entered is unique",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The not null constraint ensures that data is entered into the database. It displays an error message whenever a data field mentioned is left empty. "
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "3.\tWhat is the function of the unique constraint?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt ensures that no two values under an attribute are identical",
            "b)\tIt ensures that all the attributes are perfectly unique in their data type",
            "c)\tIt ensures that all the relations in the database have a unique set of attributes",
            "d)\tIt does not have any function in SQL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The purpose of the unique clause is to ensure that no two values under the same attribute are identical. Primary keys are unique by default. "
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "4.\tWhat is the functions of on delete cascade?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt is used to delete a tuple in a table",
            "b)\tIt is used to specify the precise attribute that needs to be deleted in a single relation.",
            "c)\tIt is used to preserve referential integrity in a relation",
            "d)\tIt is used to execute sub-queries in the from clause."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is used to preserve referential integrity in the relation. When an attribute of a relation is the foreign key in another relation, deleting it causes referential integrity problems. The on delete cascade solves this problem by forcing us to delete the foreign key first. "
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "6.\tReferential integrity constraints are also called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFunctional dependencies",
            "b)\tSubset dependencies",
            "c)\tSuperset dependencies",
            "d)\tPrimary dependencies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The check clause allows the attribute to take only those values that are explicitly specified by the user inside the parentheses after the in key word. "
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "7.\t________  is a predicate that we expect the database to always satisfy",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAssertion",
            "b)\tReason",
            "c)\tMandate",
            "d)\tVerify"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Referential integrity constraints are also called as subset dependencies. It is called so because the set of foreign key values in r1 of r2 must be a subset of the set of primary key values in r2. "
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "9.\tWhat statement is used to define a new assertion in SQL?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tcreate  check ;",
            "b)\tcreate assertion  where ;",
            "c)\tcreate  where ;",
            "d)\tcreate assertion  check ;"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An assertion is a predicate that we expect the database to always satisfy. Domain constraints and referential integrity constraints are special forms of assertions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following is not a valid Date and Time data type?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tdate",
            "b)\ttime",
            "c)\tdatestamp",
            "d)\ttimestamp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: datestamp is not a valid Date and Time data type. Timestamp exists but datestamp does not exist in SQL."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "2.\tWhat is a timestamp?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tA combination of date and time with date first",
            "b)\tA combination of date and time with time first",
            "c)\tA combination of time and place with time first",
            "d)\tA combination of time and place with place first"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A timestamp is a combination of date and time with date first.\nEg: ‘2002-04-25 10:20:04.43’."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "4.\tWhat is a default value?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt is a value that automatically creates a primary key",
            "b)\tIt is a value that cannot be altered during insertion of values in the tuple",
            "c)\tIt is a value that is initially loaded into the attribute",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The p in the parentheses indicates the number of fractional digits for seconds."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "5.\tWhich of the following is an illegal data type in SQL",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tnumber",
            "b)\tclob",
            "c)\tblob",
            "d)\tlint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A default value is a value that is initially loaded into the attribute. All the tuples have the default value in the attribute for which it is specified in case any value is not externally specified. "
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following is a privilege in SQL standard?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tselect",
            "b)\tinsert",
            "c)\tupdate",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: lint\nExplanation: clob and blob are called large object data types. They can be used to store values that can go to the size of gigabytes. Number is used to store the basic integer data type. "
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "9.\tThe _________ statement is used in SQL to confer authorization.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tgrant",
            "b)\tconfer",
            "c)\timplement",
            "d)\tpermit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SQL allows the creation of new data types using the “create type  as  final;” statement."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following is/are a function of dynamic SQL?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAllowing a program to construct an SQL query in a character string",
            "b)\tSubmitting the query",
            "c)\tRetrieving the result into the program variables a tuple at a time",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dynamic SQL allows the program to construct the queries in character string format, it submits them, and then retrieves the data into the program variables one tuple at a time."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "2.\tWhat is the full form of JDBC?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tJava Database Connectivity",
            "b)\tJava Database Co-Operation",
            "c)\tJSP Database Committee",
            "d)\tJava Database Creation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full form of JDBC is Java Database Connectivity. This full form is no longer widely used and the abbreviation is mostly used everywhere. "
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "4.\tWhich of the following are not a part of PL/SQL",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTriggers",
            "b)\tPackages",
            "c)\tFunctions",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Developers can write their own functions into SQL by using the create function statement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "5.\tThe part of SQL that deals with the SQL supports constructs is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPersistent construct dealer",
            "b)\tPersistent storage module",
            "c)\tPersistent supports center",
            "d)\tPrimary storage medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the three mentioned features i.e. triggers, functions, packages are a part of PL/SQL. "
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "6.\tA _________ is a statement that the system executes whenever a database is modified",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTrigger",
            "b)\tFunction",
            "c)\tPackage",
            "d)\tProtocol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The part of SQL that deals with the SQL supports constructs is called as Persistent Storage Module (PSM). The SQL supports construct give it almost all the power of a general purpose programming language. "
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "8.\tHow many different types of drivers are present in JDBC?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t3",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A trigger is a statement that the system executes whenever a database is modified. Immediately after the specified modification of the database is complete, the trigger statement gets executed and then the execution is continued."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich JDBC Driver is the most efficient of all the JDBC drivers?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tType 1 Driver",
            "b)\tType 2 Driver",
            "c)\tType 3 Driver",
            "d)\tType 4 Driver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Recursive queries can be used in SQL in order to verify a condition repeatedly. SQL allows recursive queries. "
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich package comprises of the core JDBC API?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tjava.sql",
            "b)\tjava.database",
            "c)\tsql.java",
            "d)\tjava.relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are four types of JDBC drivers which are named JDBC Type 1,2,3,4 drivers respectively. "
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "1.\tWhat is the full form of OLAP?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOnline Application Programming",
            "b)\tOnline Application Processing",
            "c)\tOnline Analytical programming",
            "d)\tOnline Analytical Processing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The full form of OLAP is Online Analytical Processing. It is an interactive system that gives various features to analysts."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "2.\tData that can be modelled as dimension attributes and measure attributes are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMono-dimensional data",
            "b)\tMulti-dimensional data",
            "c)\tMeasurable data",
            "d)\tEfficient data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Data that can be modelled as dimension attributes and measure attributes are called multi-dimensional data."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "3.\tThe operation of changing a dimensions used in a cross-tab is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAlteration",
            "b)\tPivoting",
            "c)\tPiloting",
            "d)\tRenewing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We can change the dimensions used in a cross tab. The operation of changing a dimensions used in a cross-tab is called as pivoting."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "4.\tThe operation of moving from finer granular data to coarser granular data is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tReduction",
            "b)\tIncrement",
            "c)\tRoll up",
            "d)\tDrill down"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: OLAP systems permit users to view the data at any level of granularity. The process of moving from finer granular data to coarser granular data is called as roll-up."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "5.\tHow many dimensions of multi-dimensional data do cross tabs enable analysts to view?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t3",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Cross-tabs enable analysts to view two dimensions of multi-dimensional data, along with the summaries of the data."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "6.\tThe  _______ function allows substitution of values in an attribute of a tuple",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCube",
            "b)\tUnknown",
            "c)\tDecode",
            "d)\tSubstitute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The decode function allows substitution of values in an attribute of a tuple. The decode function does not always work as we might like for null values because predicates on null values evaluate to unknown."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "7.\tWhich of the following OLAP systems do not exist?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tHOLAP",
            "b)\tMOLAP",
            "c)\tROLAP",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: HOLAP means Hybrid OLAP, MOLAP means multidimensional OLAP, ROLAP means relational OLAP. This means all of the above OLAP systems exist."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "9.\tThe operation of moving from coarser granular data to finer granular data is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tReduction",
            "b)\tIncrement",
            "c)\tRoll back",
            "d)\tDrill down"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: OLAP systems can be implemented as client-server systems. In fact most of the current OLAP systems are implemented as client-server systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following is not a relational algebra function?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSelect",
            "b)\tProject",
            "c)\tManipulate",
            "d)\tUnion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There does not exist any operation named as manipulate operation in relational algebra. The union gives the union of two sets. Project is similar to select in SQL and select is similar to where in SQL."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "2.\tThe select operation’s function in relational algebra is identical to the _______ clause in SQL",
        "Options": [
            "a)\twhere",
            "b)\tfrom",
            "c)\tselect",
            "d)\tnone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The select operation’s function in relational algebra is identical to the where clause in SQL standard. It is therefore used to check for a particular condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "3.\tThe project operation’s function in relational algebra is identical to the _______ clause in SQL",
        "Options": [
            "a)\twhere",
            "b)\tfrom",
            "c)\tselect",
            "d)\tnone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The project operation’s function in relational algebra is identical to the select clause in SQL standard. It is used to list the attributes that are to be displayed."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "6.\tHow is the left outer join symbol represented in relational algebra?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t⟕",
            "b)\t⟖",
            "c)\t⟗",
            "d)\t⋈"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a relational-algebra expression E has arity n, then the above expression returns the result of expression E under the name X, and with the  attributes renamed to A1 , A2 , …., An."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "7.\tHow is the right outer join symbol represented in relational algebra?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t⟕",
            "b)\t⟖",
            "c)\t⟗",
            "d)\t⋈"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The above expression finds all the tuples in loan wherever the amount is greater than 1200. Because the condition specifies that the amount should be greater than 1200."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "9.\tUpdating, Deleting and Inserting in relational algebra is done using the ________ operator",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAssignment",
            "b)\tModification",
            "c)\tAlteration",
            "d)\tInclusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The symbol of the left outer join is similar to the symbol of the natural join but it has two dashes on the top and bottom left side."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "11.\tThe collections on which aggregate functions can operate are called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMultisets",
            "b)\tMultivalues",
            "c)\tMulticollections",
            "d)\tMultivariables"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The symbol of the right outer join is similar to the symbol of the natural join but it has two dashes on the top and bottom right side."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "1.\tThe _________ of the entity set is an actual collection of entities belonging to that entity set.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tExtension",
            "b)\tIntention",
            "c)\tDescription",
            "d)\tAvailability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The extension of the entity set is an actual collection of entities belonging to that entity set. "
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "2.\tA ___________ is an association among several entities.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRelationship",
            "b)\tAssociation",
            "c)\tSet",
            "d)\tCombination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A relationship is an association among several entities. A relationship specifies how two entities are related."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "3.\tThe attributes of a relationship are called as _________ attributes",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRelational",
            "b)\tConjunctive",
            "c)\tDescriptive",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A relationship may also have attributes. These attributes are called as descriptive attributes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "4.\tWhat are composite attributes?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThey are those attributes which cannot be further divided into other attributes",
            "b)\tThey are those attributes which can further be divided into other attributes",
            "c)\tThey are those attributes which are essentially the primary keys of the relation",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Composite attributes are the ones which can be further divided into other attributes whereas simple attributes cannot be divided into other attributes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "5.\tLet E be an entity set in a relationship set R. If every entity in E participates in at least one relationships in R, Then the participation of E in R is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPartial",
            "b)\tTotal",
            "c)\tComplete",
            "d)\tIncomplete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: Total\nExplanation: Let E be an entity set in a relationship set R. If every entity in E participates in at least one relation in R, Then the participation of E in R is total. "
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "6.\tLet E be an entity set in a relationship set R. If only some entities in E participate in relationships in R, Then the participation of E in R is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPartial",
            "b)\tTotal",
            "c)\tComplete",
            "d)\tIncomplete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: Total\nExplanation: Let E be an entity set in a relationship set R. If only some entities in E participate in relationships in R, Then the participation of E in R is partial. "
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich of the following is a good database management practice?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAdding redundant attributes",
            "b)\tRemoving redundant attributes",
            "c)\tNot specifying primary keys",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Keys can be specified in the entity-relationship model to uniquely identify the entity in the entity set. "
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following symbols represent entity sets in an ER diagram?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDivided rectangles",
            "b)\tDiamonds",
            "c)\tLines",
            "d)\tUndivided rectangles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rectangles divided into two parts represent entity sets in an ER diagram. The upper rectangle contains the name of the entity sets. And the lower rectangle contains the attributes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "2.\t Which of the following symbols represent relationship sets in an ER diagram",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDivided rectangles",
            "b)\tDiamonds",
            "c)\tLines",
            "d)\tUndivided rectangles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Diamonds represent relationship sets in an ER diagram. Relationship sets define how two entity sets are related in a database."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "3.\tWhat do double diamonds represent in an ER diagram",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThey link entity sets to relationship sets",
            "b)\tTotal participation of an entity in a relationship set",
            "c)\tRelationship sets linked to weak entity sets",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The double diamonds represent the relationship sets linked to weak entity sets. Weak entity sets are the sets that do not have a primary key. "
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "4.\tWhat does a directed line ( →  )  from a relationship set to two entity sets mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOne-one",
            "b)\tMany-one",
            "c)\tMany-many",
            "d)\tOne-many"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A directed line ( →  )  from a relationship set to two entity sets means that there is a one-one cardinality between two entity sets. "
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "5.\tHow are roles specified in an ER diagram",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBy labelling the rectangles",
            "b)\tBy labelling the diamonds",
            "c)\tRoles cannot be specified in an ER diagram",
            "d)\tBy labelling the lines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: E-R diagrams can include role indicators. Roles can be specified in an ER diagram by labelling the lines. "
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "6.\tHow is the discriminator of a weak entity set specified?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUsing a solid line",
            "b)\tCircling it",
            "c)\tUsing a dashed line",
            "d)\tDrawing a square around it"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A discriminator of a weak entity set can be specified by underlining it with a dashed line. "
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "7.\tAn entity set that has a primary key is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tStrong entity set",
            "b)\tWeak entity set",
            "c)\tComplete entity set",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An entity set that has a primary key is called as a strong entity set. An entity set that does not have a primary key is called a weak entity set. "
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "8.\tThe relationship associating the weak entity sets with the identifying entity set is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIdentifying relationship",
            "b)\tConnecting relationship",
            "c)\tCompleting relationship",
            "d)\tUnique relationship"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The relationship associating the weak entity sets with the identifying entity set is called as an Identifying relationship. An identifying set is a many to one from the weak entity set to the identifying entity set. "
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "1.\tFor schemas derived from strong entity sets, the _______ of the entity set serves as the primary key of the resulting schema",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFirst attribute",
            "b)\tPrimary key",
            "c)\tForeign key",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For schemas derived from strong entity sets, the primary key of the entity set serves as the primary key of the resulting schema. This is because the primary keys are to be preserved as they are unique."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "3.\tThe primary key of the representation of a weak entity set consists of the primary key of the strong entity set and the _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDiscriminator of the weak entity set",
            "b)\tForeign key",
            "c)\tPrimary key of all the other entity sets",
            "d)\tAll the attributes of the weak entity set"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Derived attributes cannot be directly represented in the relational data model. Instead, they are represented as methods. "
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "4.\tFor a binary many to many relationship, the ________ of the participating entity sets becomes the prime attribute",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIntersection of primary keys",
            "b)\tPrimary key of either one",
            "c)\tUnion of primary keys",
            "d)\tPrimary key on the many side"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The primary key of the representation of a weak entity set consists of the primary key of the strong entity set and the discriminator of the weak entity set. "
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "5.\tFor a binary one to one relationship, the ________ of the participating entity sets becomes the prime attribute",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIntersection of primary keys",
            "b)\tPrimary key of either one",
            "c)\tUnion of primary keys",
            "d)\tPrimary key on the many side"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For a binary many to many relationship, the union of the primary keys of the participating entity sets becomes the prime attribute. "
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "6.\tFor a binary many to many relationship, the ________ of the participating entity sets becomes the prime attribute",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIntersection of primary keys",
            "b)\tPrimary key of either one",
            "c)\tUnion of primary keys",
            "d)\tPrimary key on the many side"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a binary one to one relationship, the primary key of either one of the participating entity sets becomes the prime attribute."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "7.\tFor a n-ary relationship set without arrows, the ________ of the participating entity sets becomes the prime attribute",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIntersection of primary keys",
            "b)\tPrimary key of either one",
            "c)\tUnion of primary keys",
            "d)\tPrimary key on the many side"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For a binary many to many relationship, the primary key on the many side of the participating entity sets becomes the prime attribute."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich of the following can affect the placement of the relationship attributes?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAlphabetical order",
            "b)\tThe data in the attribute",
            "c)\tCardinality ratio",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For a binary many to many relationship, the union of the primary keys of the participating entity sets becomes the prime attribute. "
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "1.\tThe process of designating sub groupings within the entity set is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSpecialization",
            "b)\tDivision",
            "c)\tAggregation",
            "d)\tFinalization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The process of designating sub-groupings within the entity set is called as specialization. Specialization allows us to distinguish among entities. "
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich of the following is the specialization that permits multiple sets",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSuperclass specialization",
            "b)\tDisjoint specialization",
            "c)\tOverlapping specialization",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  We can apply specialization multiple times to refine a design. An entity set may also be specialized by more than one distinguishing feature. "
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "4.\tThe similarities between the entity set can be expressed by which of the following features?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSpecialization",
            "b)\tGeneralization",
            "c)\tUniquation",
            "d)\tInheritance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Overlapping specialization is the type of specialization that permits multiple sets. But disjoint specialization does not permit multiple sets. Disjoint specialization permits at most one set."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "5.\tHigher level entity sets are designated by the term _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSub class",
            "b)\tSuper class",
            "c)\tParent class",
            "d)\tRoot class"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The similarities between the entity set can be expressed by the generalization feature. It is a containment o the relationship that exists between a higher level entity set and one or more lower level entity sets."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "7.\tWhich of the following is not a generalization constraint?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCondition-defined",
            "b)\tUser defined",
            "c)\tDisjoint",
            "d)\tMachine defined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Higher level entity sets can also be designated by the term super class. In the similar manner lower level entity sets can also be designated by the term sub class. "
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "8.\tCondition defined generalization constraint is also said to be ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAttribute defined",
            "b)\tConstraint defined",
            "c)\tValue defined",
            "d)\tUndefined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The attributes of the higher level entity sets are inherited by the attributes of the lower level entity sets. But the inverse is not true in this case. "
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "9.\tIf each higher level entity belongs to the lower level entity, then what kind of generalization is it?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tModal generalization",
            "b)\tPartial generalization",
            "c)\tTotal generalization",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Machine definition is not a generalization constraint. Condition defined, user defined, disjoint and overlapping are 4 generalization constraints. "
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "10.\t________ is an abstraction through which relationships are treated as higher level entities",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCreation",
            "b)\tSuperseding",
            "c)\tAttribute separation",
            "d)\tAggregation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Condition defined generalization constraint is also said to be attribute defined."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following is not a feature of a good relational design?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSpecifying primary keys",
            "b)\tSpecifying foreign keys",
            "c)\tPreserving integrity constraints",
            "d)\tAllowing redundancy of attributes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Allowing redundancy of attributes makes it very difficult for data extraction. So, It is not a good relational design feature. "
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "2.\tThe dependency rules specified by the database designer are known as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDesigner dependencies",
            "b)\tDatabase rules",
            "c)\tFunctional dependencies",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The dependency rules specified by the database designer are known as functional dependencies. The normal forms are based on functional dependencies. "
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "3.\tIf the decomposition is unable to represent certain important facts about the relation, then such a decomposition is called as?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLossless decomposition",
            "b)\tLossy decomposition",
            "c)\tInsecure decomposition",
            "d)\tSecure decomposition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the decomposition is unable to represent certain important facts about the relation, then such a decomposition is called as lossy decomposition. Lossy decompositions should be avoided as they result in the loss of data. "
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "4.\tIf the decomposition is able to represent all the facts about the relation then such a decomposition is called as?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLossless decomposition",
            "b)\tLossy decomposition",
            "c)\tInsecure decomposition",
            "d)\tSecure decomposition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the decomposition is able to represent all the facts about the relation then such a decomposition is called as a lossless decomposition. Lossless decompositions are generally preferred. "
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "5.\tA domain whose elements are indivisible is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUnique domain",
            "b)\tProxy domain",
            "c)\tAtomic domain",
            "d)\tMultiple domain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A domain is said to be atomic if all of its elements are considered to be indivisible. If the domains are atomic, then the relational schema is in the first normal form. "
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "6.\tIf all the domains are atomic then the relational schema is in ________ normal form",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t3",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If all the domains are atomic then the relational schema is in first (1) normal form. That is, the domains must be indivisible. "
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "1.\tAn instance of a relation that satisfies all real world constraints is known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tProper relation",
            "b)\tIdeal relation",
            "c)\tPerfect relation",
            "d)\tLegal relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A relation that satisfies all the real world constraints is called as a legal relation. An instance of a legal relation is called as a legal instance. "
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "2.\tIf K → R then K is said to be the _______ of R",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCandidate key",
            "b)\tForeign key",
            "c)\tSuper key",
            "d)\tDomain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If K →  R then k is said to be the superkey of R i.e. K uniquely identifies every tuple in the relation R. "
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "3.\tX →  Y holds on a schema k(K) if?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAt least one legal instance satisfies the functional dependency",
            "b)\tNo legal instance satisfies the functional dependency",
            "c)\tEach and every legal instance satisfies the functional dependency",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: X →  Y holds on a schema k(K) if each and every legal instance satisfies the functional dependency. Even if one instance does not satisfy the functional dependency X→ Y does not hold on a schema. "
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "4.\tX→ Y is trivial if?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tX ⊂ Y",
            "b)\tY ⊂ X",
            "c)\tX ⊇ Y",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: X→ Y is said to be trivial if X is a subset of Y. Thus X ⊂ Y implies X→Y is trivial."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "5.\tWhich of the following is not a condition for X→  Y in Boyce codd normal form?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tX →  Y is trivial",
            "b)\tX is the superkey for the relational schema R",
            "c)\tY is the superkey for the relational schema R",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Y does not need to be a superkey of the relation for the given functional dependency to satisfy BCNF. X→ Y must be trivial and X must be the superkey of the relation R. "
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "6.\tWhich of the following is used to express database consistency?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPrimary keys",
            "b)\tFunctional dependencies",
            "c)\tCheck clause",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Primary keys, Functional dependencies, Check clause are all used to express database consistency. "
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "7.\tWhich of the following is not a condition for the third normal form in the case of XY?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tX→ Y is trivial",
            "b)\tX is the superkey for R",
            "c)\tEach attribute in Y-X is a candidate key for R",
            "d)\tEach attribute in X-Y is a candidate key for R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Each attribute in X-Y is a candidate key for R is not a necessary condition for the third normal form in the case of X →  Y. X→Y is trivial and X is the superkey of R are necessary conditions for the third normal form. "
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "8.\tF+  is called as the ________ of F",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tClosure",
            "b)\tSum",
            "c)\tCartesian product",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: F+ is called as the closure of F. It contains all the possible combinations of a functional dependency set in it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "1.\tA functional dependency f on R is _______  by a set of functional dependencies F on r if every instance of r(R) that satisfies f also satisfies F.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLogically Defined",
            "b)\tLogically Derived",
            "c)\tLogically implied",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given a set F of functional dependencies on a schema, we can prove that certain other functional dependencies also hold on that schema. We say such FDs are logically implied by F. A functional dependency f on R is logically implied by a set of functional dependencies F on r if every instance of r(R) that satisfies F also satisfies f. "
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "2.\tIf F is a set of functional dependencies, then the closure of F is denoted by?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tF*",
            "b)\tFo",
            "c)\tF+",
            "d)\tF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If F is a set of functional dependencies, then the closure of F is denoted by F+. It is the set of all functional dependencies logically implied by F. "
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "3.\tIf a functional dependency is reflexive, B is a subset of A and A is the set of attributes, then",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tB→A holds",
            "b)\tA→B holds",
            "c)\tAB→C holds",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a functional dependency is reflexive, B is a subset of A and A is the set of attributes, then A→B holds. This is called the reflexivity rule of Armstrong’s axioms. "
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "5.\tArmstrong axioms are called sound because?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThey are expensive",
            "b)\tThey cannot generate correct functional dependencies",
            "c)\tThey allow us to generate the complete closure",
            "d)\tThey cannot generate incorrect functional dependencies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Armstrong’s axioms allow us to generate all F+ for any given F and hence are called complete. "
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "7.\tIf A→B, A→ C then which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tA→BC",
            "b)\tA→B",
            "c)\tA→C",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Armstrong’s axioms are called as sound axioms because they do not generate incorrect functional dependencies. "
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "8.\tIf B is an attribute and A→B, Then B is said to be ________ by a.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLogically implied",
            "b)\tFunctionally implied",
            "c)\tLogically determined",
            "d)\tFunctionally determined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All functional dependencies are transitive. This is the transitivity rule of Armstrong’s axioms."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "9.\tWe say that a decomposition having the property F’+ = F+ is a __________ decomposition.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDependency losing",
            "b)\tDependency preserving",
            "c)\tLossless",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Applying the union rule to the given question, we get, A→BC is true. The other two options are specified in the question itself. "
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "10.\tA  _________ Fc for F is a set of dependencies such that F logically implies all dependencies in Fc, and Fc logically implies all dependencies in F.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCanonical cover",
            "b)\tComplete cover",
            "c)\tCanonical dependency",
            "d)\tCanonical clause"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If B is an attribute and A→B, Then B is said to be functionally determined by a. "
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "1.\tWhat does the BCNF decomposition algorithm do?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tStates a method to decompose a relation satisfying BCNF",
            "b)\tStates a method for joining two relations satisfying BCNF",
            "c)\tStates a method to decompose a relational schema such that there are no multiple occurrences",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If a relation is not in BCNF, it can be decomposed into simpler relations that are in BCNF. The BCNF decomposition algorithm states a method to decompose a relation satisfying BCNF. "
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "2.\tThe 3NF decomposition algorithm is also called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t3NF normal algorithm",
            "b)\t3NF synthesis algorithm",
            "c)\t3NF generator",
            "d)\tFunctional dependence algorithm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The 3NF decomposition algorithm is also called as 3NF synthesis algorithm since it takes a set of dependencies and adds one schema at a time, instead of decomposing the initial schema repeatedly. "
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich of the following is desirable in a database design with functional dependencies?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBCNF",
            "b)\tLosslessness",
            "c)\tDependency preservation",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: A good database design must satisfy BCNF, must be lossless, must be dependency preserving. These are the goals of database design with functional dependency."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "6.\tMulti valued dependencies are also called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tEquality generating dependencies",
            "b)\tTuple generating dependencies",
            "c)\tMulti-purpose dependencies",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SQL does not specify a way to mention functional dependencies. Functional dependencies are just used for theoretical improvement of database while implementing them in SQL later. "
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "7.\tFunctional dependencies are sometimes referred to as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tEquality generating dependencies",
            "b)\tTuple generating dependencies",
            "c)\tMulti-purpose dependencies",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Most current database systems do not support constraints on materialized view. "
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "8.\tThe _______ is a set of all functional and multi values dependencies implied by a set of functional dependencies",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tStar",
            "b)\tClosure",
            "c)\tDerivation",
            "d)\tEvolution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Multi valued dependencies are also called as tuple generating dependencies because they require other tuples of a certain form to be present in the relation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "9.\tState true or false: If a relational schema is in _______ NF and A is a subset of R and B is also a subset of R then it is that A is a superkey is a trivial multi values dependency.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t1",
            "b)\t2",
            "c)\t3",
            "d)\t4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Functional dependencies are sometimes referred to as equality generating dependencies because they require other tuples of a certain form to be present in the relation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich of the following normal forms does not exist?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBCNF",
            "b)\tPJNF",
            "c)\t5NF",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The closure is a set of all functional and multi values dependencies implied by a set of functional dependencies on a given relation. It is denoted by giving a “+” superscript. "
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following is not a process of generating a good relational schema?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConverting ER diagrams to relational schema",
            "b)\tDecomposing the relational schema while satisfying functional dependencies",
            "c)\tJoining multiple relations together to form a single relation containing all the attributes",
            "d)\tA design of relations which is then tested and modified to satisfy given normal forms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Joining multiple relations together to form a single relation containing all the attributes is not a method for the development of good relational schema because it might violate the normal forms if it is combined. "
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "2.\tWhat is unique role assumption?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe attribute name has a unique meaning in the database",
            "b)\tThe attributes are all unique",
            "c)\tNo two tuples have even a single same value in a relation",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Unique role assumption means that the attribute names must have unique meaning in the database. This prevents us from using the same attribute to mean different things in different schemas. "
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "3.\tThe process of making a normalized schema unnormalized is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUnnormalization",
            "b)\tDenormalization",
            "c)\tRenormalization",
            "d)\tAnnormalization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process of making a normalized schema unnormalized is called as denormalization. Designers use it to tune performance of systems to support time-critical operations."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "5.\tThe data that have a time interval associated with them during which they are valid are called as  ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTimed data",
            "b)\tTemporal data",
            "c)\tModel data",
            "d)\tClocked data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Crosstabs may be useful for the users but they are not desirable in a database system because the queries would get more complicated due to the addition of cross tabs."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "6.\tThe value of the data at a particular time is called as?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInstance",
            "b)\tPicture",
            "c)\tSnapshot",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The data that have a time interval associated with them during which they are valid are called as Temporal data. We use the term snapshot to mean the value of the data at a particular point in time. "
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "7.\tFunctional dependencies that have a time associated with them during which they are valid are called as________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTimed functional dependencies",
            "b)\tClocked functional dependencies",
            "c)\tTemporal functional dependencies",
            "d)\tModeled functional dependencies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of the data at a particular time is called as a snapshot. This is used in temporal data. "
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich of the following is the time of temporal data that record when a fact was recorded in a database?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTransaction time",
            "b)\tValid time",
            "c)\tEnter time",
            "d)\tExit time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Functional dependencies that have a time associated with them during which they are valid are called as temporal functional dependencies. All snapshots of the relation should satisfy the functional dependency for it to be a temporal functional dependency. "
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "10.\tTo specify the foreign keys in relations referencing temporal data we need to specify _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe time interval",
            "b)\tThe Boolean value for the working",
            "c)\tThe integer corresponding to the relation number",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IF a system supports a native valid time type, then the system can detect and prevent overlapping time intervals."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "1.\tBrowsers use a standardized syntax called?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTCP/IP",
            "b)\tHTML",
            "c)\tXML",
            "d)\tJava"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Hypertext Markup Language [HTML] is the standardized syntax used by the browsers which supports formatted information as well as forms based interfaces. "
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "2.\tA ______ is a globally unique name for every document that can be accessed on the Web",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tID",
            "b)\tUCL",
            "c)\tURL",
            "d)\tUML"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  A URL (Uniform resource locator) is a globally unique name for every document that can be accessed on the Web."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "3.\tWhat is the full form of HTTP?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tHyper Text Trial Program",
            "b)\tHyper Text Transfer Protocol",
            "c)\tHyper Text Technology Protocol",
            "d)\tHyper Text Trial Protocol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: HTTP – Hyper Text Transfer Protocol. This is aprotocol for transferring HTML documents. "
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "4.\tA ______ is a program running on the server which accepts requests from a browser and sends HTML documents",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tWeb server",
            "b)\tWeb transmitter",
            "c)\tWeb intermediate",
            "d)\tWeb multitasker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A Web Server is a program running on the server which accepts requests from a browser and sends HTML documents. The browser and the web server communicate via HTTP. "
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "5.\tWhat is the use of CGI?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt specifies the path of data transfer",
            "b)\tIt specifies how the server communicates with the application programs",
            "c)\tIt charts out error handling procedures in case an error arises",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CGI specifies how the server communicates with application programs. The application program communicates with a database server in order to get data. "
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "6.\tThe extra information of a site maintained at the client end is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCookie",
            "b)\tPassword",
            "c)\tHistory",
            "d)\tSessions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The extra information of a site maintained at the client end is called as cookie. It is a small piece of text containing identifying information with an associated name. "
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "8.\tWhat is the full form of CGI?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCommon graphics interface",
            "b)\tCommon gateway interface",
            "c)\tCommon gateway internet",
            "d)\tCommon gateway information"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: HTTP is connectionless because most computer have a limit on the simultaneous connections they can accommodate. If this limit is exceeded then access is denied to further users. "
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich of the following functions are done by a web server?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAccept requests from a web browser",
            "b)\tSends back results in HTML",
            "c)\tExecutes programs with arguments supplied by the user",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The full form of CGI is Common Gateway Interface. This defines how a web server communicates with an application program. "
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "10.\tWhat is the function of the cascading style sheet",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAllows us to edit the HTML document",
            "b)\tIt is an IDE that allows us to write HTML codes more efficiently",
            "c)\tIt allows us to use the same style on multiple HTML documents",
            "d)\tIt acts as an intermediary to provide a variety of information services"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A web server accepts requests from a web browser and sends back results in HTML. The most important feature of a web server is to execute programs with arguments supplied by the user. "
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "1.\tThe _______ specification defines an application programming interface for communication between the server and the application program",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tJava Servlet",
            "b)\tJDBC",
            "c)\tJava Applet",
            "d)\tJava Swing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The java servlet specification defines an application programming interface for communication between the server and the application program. The HttpServlet class in Java implements the servlet API specification. "
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich of these functions is not a part of the servlet lifecycle",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tChecking if an instance of servlet exists or not",
            "b)\tInvoking the service method of the servlet",
            "c)\tShutting down the servlet",
            "d)\tPausing the servlet for a given period of time."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Servlets are used to generate dynamic responses to HTTP requests. The task of a servlet is to process a request dynamically. "
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "4.\tWhich of the following application servers do not provide built in support for servlets?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTomcat server",
            "b)\tGlassfish",
            "c)\tJBoss",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pausing the servlet for a given amount of time is not a part of the servlet lifecycle. A servlet can be checked, invoked and destroyed but it cannot be paused. "
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "5.\tWhat is the full form of JSP?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tJava servlet program",
            "b)\tJava server pages",
            "c)\tJava server pages",
            "d)\tJava server program"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All of the mentioned application servers provide built in support for servlets. Glassfish and Tomcat are the most prominently used application servers. "
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "6.\tWhile using Javascript, the browser parses the HTML code into a tree like structure defined by a standard called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDOS",
            "b)\tDOD",
            "c)\tDOM",
            "d)\tDON"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The full form of JSP is Java Server Pages. It is a scripting language that allows HTML programmers to mix static HTML with dynamically generated HTML. "
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "7.\tJavascript is used to create dynamic webpages using technologies that are collectively called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAjax",
            "b)\tThor",
            "c)\tDynamo",
            "d)\tAchilles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: While using Javascript, the browser parses the HTML code into a tree like structure defined by a standard called Document Object Model (DOM). Javascript code can modify the tree structure to carry out certain operations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "8.\tWhat are scripting languages?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe programming languages that pre decide the web page content",
            "b)\tThe programming languages that are simpler and offer same protection",
            "c)\tThe programming languages that trade off simplicity for protection.",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Javascript is used to create dynamic webpages using technologies that are collectively called Ajax. "
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "9.\tWhat are client side scripting languages?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe languages designed to be executed on the client’s web browser",
            "b)\tThe languages designed to be executed on the server",
            "c)\tThe languages designed to reduce the amount of data costs incurred at the client end",
            "d)\tThe languages designed to be executed in multiple computers paralleled with each other"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Scripting languages are those languages that are simpler with enriched user interface features but offer the same protection as that of Java. "
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following is true regarding the model-view- controller architecture?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe model corresponds to the business logic layer",
            "b)\tThe view defines the presentation of data",
            "c)\tThe controller receives events, executes actions on the model and returns a view",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the model-view-controller architecture, the model corresponds to the business logic layer, the view defines the way data is presented and the controller receives events, executes actions on the model and returns a view. "
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "2.\tThe ___________ provides a high level view of data and actions on data",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBusiness-logic layer",
            "b)\tData access layer",
            "c)\tData transfer layer",
            "d)\tBusiness manager layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Business-logic layer provides a high level view of data and actions on data. An object oriented approach is used to code this layer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "3.\tThe _________ layer provides the interface between the business logic layer and the underlying database",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBusiness-logic layer",
            "b)\tData access layer",
            "c)\tData transfer layer",
            "d)\tBusiness manager layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The data-access layer provides the interface between the business logic layer and the underlying database. The data access layer provides the mapping from the object oriented data model to the relational model. "
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "4.\tWhat are workflows in a business logic layer?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThey describe how a particular task that involves servers is handled",
            "b)\tThey describe how multiple tasks involving a single participant is handled",
            "c)\tThey describe how a particular task involving multiple participants is handled.",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Business logic includes workflows. Workflows in a business logic layer describe how a particular task involving multiple participants is handled. "
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "6.\tWhat is the full form of JSON?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tJavaScript Object Native",
            "b)\tJavaScript Object Notation",
            "c)\tJavaScript Object Negation",
            "d)\tJava Object Notation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The code implementing the actions in the business logic layer ensures that business rules are followed. For example a student can only enroll in a course if the prerequisites are completed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "7.\tWhich of the following features does Rapid Application Development possess?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tProvide a library of functions to generate UI elements",
            "b)\tProvide drag and drop features in a n IDE",
            "c)\tAuto generation of code for the user interface from a declarative specification",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: JSON – JavaScript Object Notation. This is an encoding for javascript objects. "
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following is not a web application development framework feature?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAn object oriented model",
            "b)\tA declarative way of specifying a form with validation constraints",
            "c)\tCreating mass servers for effective handling of data",
            "d)\tA template scripting system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main features of Rapid Application development are to provide a library of functions for GUI development, to provide drag and drop features in an IDE, Auto-generation of code for the user interface from a declarative specification. "
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "9.\tWhat are report generators?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThey are the tools to generate human readable reports from a database",
            "b)\tThey are the tools that generate reports on the statistics of the database usage",
            "c)\tThey are the tools that prevent database querying and instead they generate pie charts and graphs",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Creating mass servers for effective handling of data is not a part of the web application development framework feature. "
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich of the following methods is used to reduce overhead?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConnection pooling",
            "b)\tParallel Processing",
            "c)\tCaching Query Results at the server",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Report generators are the tools to generate human readable reports from a database. They integrate querying the database with the creation of formatted text and summary charts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "1.\tIf an attacker manages to get an application to execute an SQL query created by the attacker, then such attacks are called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSQL attacks",
            "b)\tSQL injection attacks",
            "c)\tSQL usage attack",
            "d)\tSQL destroyer attack"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If an attacker manages to get an application to execute an SQL query created by the attacker, then such attacks are called as SQL injection attacks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "2.\tAn attack on a website that stores and displays text to a user is known as ______ attack",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSQL attack",
            "b)\tXSS attack",
            "c)\tXRP attack",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An attack on a website that stores and displays text to a user is known as XSS attack. It is called as cross site scripting attack. "
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "3.\tThe URL of the page that had the link that the user clicked to access the page is called as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSource",
            "b)\tLinker",
            "c)\tLeaker",
            "d)\tReferrer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The URL of the page that had the link that the user clicked to access the page is called as referrer. The HTTP protocol allows the server to check the referrer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "5.\tThe system where two independent pieces of data are used to identify a user is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTwo system authentication",
            "b)\tID password authentication",
            "c)\tTwo factor authentication",
            "d)\tMulti data authentication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Password leakage is a major security problem because the leaked password grants access to malicious visitors. "
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "6.\tWhat are man in the middle attacks?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUsers are forced to use a second server which causes the attack",
            "b)\tUsers are forced to divert to a fake site where the attack takes place",
            "c)\tUsers are fooled by similar GUI and data is extracted from them.",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The system where two independent pieces of data are used to identify a user is called as two-factor authentication. The two factors should not share a common vulnerability. "
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "7.\tWhat are phishing attacks?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUsers are forced to use a second server which causes the attack",
            "b)\tUsers are forced to divert to a fake site where the attack takes place",
            "c)\tUsers are fooled by similar GUI and data is extracted from them.",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Man in the middle attacks are those attacks in which the users are forced to divert to a fake site where the attack takes place. The fake site is then used to obtain the data from the user. "
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "8.\tWhat is the standard for exchanging authentication and authorization information between two different security domains?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSABM",
            "b)\tSTML",
            "c)\tSPTA",
            "d)\tSAML"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Phishing attacks are those attacks in which users are fooled by similar GUI and data is extracted from them. The fake site is then used to obtain the data from the user. "
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "9.\tA log of all changes to the application data is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAudit trail",
            "b)\tAudit log",
            "c)\tAudit lead",
            "d)\tData log"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: SAML (Security assertion Markup Language) is the standard for exchanging authentication and authorization information between two different security domains. This provides a cross-organization sign-on. "
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich of the following is a valid encryption technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tParallel key encryption",
            "b)\tPublic key encryption",
            "c)\tSystematic key encryption",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A log of all changes to the application data is called as audit trail. This helps us maintain security as it tracks all the breaches on the system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "2.\tWhat is the difference between flash memory and main memory?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tData is retained in flash memory",
            "b)\tData access is faster in flash memory",
            "c)\tData storage is very large in flash memory",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cache storage is very fast but it is the costliest form of storage. "
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "3.\tWhat is the full form of USB?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUniversal Serial Binary",
            "b)\tUniversal Storage Base",
            "c)\tUniversal Serial Bus",
            "d)\tUninterrupted Service Bus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Data is retained in flash memory. Power losses do not affect the data stored in flash memory."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "4.\tDVD is a form of ______ storage",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMagnetic storage",
            "b)\tUSB storage",
            "c)\tTape storage",
            "d)\tOptical storage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: USB – Universal Serial Bus. This is currently the most popular and convenient way of data transmittal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "5.\tWhich of the following is a part of the Magnetic disk assembly?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSpindle",
            "b)\tRead write head",
            "c)\tArm",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DVD is a form of optical storage. The data on a DVD is read by an optical reader. "
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "6.\tWhen a large number of disks are connected by a high speed network to a number of server computers, it is known as ________ architecture",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tStorage area network",
            "b)\tHigh performance network",
            "c)\tMultiple disk network",
            "d)\tLocal area network"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a magnetic disk assembly, Spindle is the central cylindrical rod, Read write head is used to read and write data and the arm is used to hold the magnetic disk. "
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "7.\tThe time from when a read or write request is issued to when the actual data transfer begins is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSeek time",
            "b)\tAccess time",
            "c)\tAverage latency time",
            "d)\tData transfer rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a large number of disks are connected by a high speed network to a number of server computers, it is known as Storage Area Network (SAN) architecture. These disks are usually arranged by a local organization technique called RAID. "
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "8.\tThe time for repositioning the arm is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSeek time",
            "b)\tAccess time",
            "c)\tReposition time",
            "d)\tLatency time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The time from when a read or write request is issued to when the actual data transfer begins is called access time. Data transfer rate is the rate at which data can be retrieved from the storage. "
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich of the following is a measure of reliability of a disk?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSeek time",
            "b)\tAverage latency time",
            "c)\tMean time to failure",
            "d)\tAverage seek time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time for repositioning the arm is called as Seek time."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "10.\tWhat is buffering?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe blocks read from disk are directly accessed",
            "b)\tThe blocks read from disk are temporarily stored in a memory",
            "c)\tThe blocks read from disk are organized in a particular fashion to cater requests.",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mean time to failure is the measure of the reliability of a disk. It gives the mean of the times that most disks last. "
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "11.\tWhat is an NVRAM?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRAM which is non-volatile in nature",
            "b)\tRAM whose data is not lost during power failures",
            "c)\tRAM that significantly speeds up data transfers",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Buffering involves reading the data and storing it in a temporary memory location called as the data buffer for future requests. The data in the buffer is temporary and is deleted after usage. "
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "12.\tFiles that support log disks are called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLogging file systems",
            "b)\tJorte File Systems",
            "c)\tJournaling File Systems",
            "d)\tChannelizing File Systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A non-volatile random access memory or NVRAM is the one which is non-volatile, data is retained during power failure and which considerably speeds up the disk writes."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "14.\tThe logical to physical page mapping is represented in a ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLogic physical table",
            "b)\tTransition table",
            "c)\tWear leveling table",
            "d)\tLogic log table"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Files that support log disks are called as Journaling File Systems. Journaling file systems can be implemented without a separate log disk, keeping the data and the log on the same disk. "
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "1.\tWhat is the full form of RAID?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRedundant Array of Independent Disks",
            "b)\tReliable Array of Independent Disks",
            "c)\tRedundant Asset Increment Data",
            "d)\tReliable Aggravation of Immaculate Data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full form of RAID is Redundant array of Independent Disks. This disk organization technique improves performance and reliability. "
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "2.\tThe process of duplicating every disk is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIncremention",
            "b)\tArraying",
            "c)\tMirroring",
            "d)\tReflecting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The simplest technique to introduce redundancy is to duplicate every disk. This process is known as Mirroring."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "4.\tData striping by splitting bits across multiple disks is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRAID striping",
            "b)\tArray striping",
            "c)\tBit level striping",
            "d)\tBlock level striping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using RAID enables us to use multiple disks which when combined together increase the mean time to failure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "5.\tHow many levels of RAID exist?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t5",
            "b)\t6",
            "c)\t7",
            "d)\t8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Data striping by splitting bits across multiple disks is called as bit level striping. For example if we have an array of 8 disks, we write bit I of each byte to disk i. "
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "6.\tRAID level 0 refers to?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDisk arrays with striping at the level of blocks",
            "b)\tDisk mirroring with block striping",
            "c)\tMemory style error correcting code",
            "d)\tBlock interleaved distributed parity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There exist a total of 7 RAID levels ranging from 0 to 6."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "7.\tRAID level 1 refers to?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDisk arrays with striping at the level of blocks",
            "b)\tDisk mirroring with block striping",
            "c)\tMemory style error correcting code",
            "d)\tBlock interleaved distributed parity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RAID level 0 refers to Disk arrays with striping at the level of blocks. This level does not have any redundancy. "
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "8.\tRAID level 2 refers to?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDisk arrays with striping at the level of blocks",
            "b)\tDisk mirroring with block striping",
            "c)\tMemory style error correcting code",
            "d)\tBlock interleaved distributed parity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RAID level 1 refers to Disk mirroring with block striping. This is also called as RAID 10 or RAID 1+0. "
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "9.\tRAID level 5 refers to?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDisk arrays with striping at the level of blocks",
            "b)\tDisk mirroring with block striping",
            "c)\tMemory style error correcting code",
            "d)\tBlock interleaved distributed parity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RAID level 2 refers to Memory style error correcting code. Memory systems have long parity bits for error detection and correction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich of the factors need not be taken into consideration while choosing a RAID level?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMonetary cost",
            "b)\tI/O requirements",
            "c)\tPerformance when the disk has failed",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: RAID level 5 refers to Block interleaved distributed parity. It partitions both the data and parity among N+1 disks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "1.\tWhat is the approximate storage capacity of CDs in MB",
        "Options": [
            "a)\t300",
            "b)\t700",
            "c)\t1100",
            "d)\t1500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanations: CDs generally have a storage capacity of 700 Megabytes and DVDs have a storage capacity of around 4.7 Gigabytes."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "2.\tThe devices that store a lot of optical disks are called as",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOptical reservoirs",
            "b)\tJukeboxes",
            "c)\tKaraoke machines",
            "d)\tSequential access machines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Jukeboxes are the devices that store a lot of optical disks and load them automatically on demand. "
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich of the following is true about file header?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt is allocated at the beginning of the file",
            "b)\tIt has information about the file",
            "c)\tIt generally contains the address of the first record in it",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A file header is a certain number of bytes allocated at the beginning of the file. It contains a variety of information about the file and it can be used to point the first record by storing the address of the first record in it."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "4.\tHow can variable length records arise in a file",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tStorage of multiple record types in a file",
            "b)\tRecord types that allow variable lengths for one or more fields",
            "c)\tRecord types that allow repeating fields, such as arrays or multisets",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Variable length records arise in a system in several ways like, Storage of multiple record types in a file. Record types that allow variable lengths for one or more fields. Record types that allow repeating fields, such as arrays or multisets. "
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "5.\tWhat does a null bitmap indicate?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe database does not exist",
            "b)\tThe record does not exist",
            "c)\tThe attributes of a record do not have a value",
            "d)\tThe attributes are missing from record"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A null-bitmap indicates that the attributes of a particular record have null values. "
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "7.\tThe linked list formed by the deleted records is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDelete list",
            "b)\tFree list",
            "c)\tNull list",
            "d)\tNon-existent list"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Variable length records can be implemented in databases. There are different techniques to implement variable length records. "
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "8.\tThe slotted page structure is used for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOrganizing records in a block",
            "b)\tOrganizing blocks in a database",
            "c)\tDeleting records from a block",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the addresses can be thought of as pointers, the deleted records thus form a linked list. The linked list formed by the deleted records is called as a free list. "
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "9.\tThe header in the slotted page structure does not contain which of the following data?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe number of record entries in the header",
            "b)\tThe end of free space in a block",
            "c)\tThe size of all the records put together in the header",
            "d)\tAn array containing location and size of each record"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slotted page structure is used for organizing records in a block. The slotted page structure contains a header at the beginning of each block. "
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "1.\tWhat is heap file organization?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAny record can be placed wherever there is a space for the record",
            "b)\tRecords are stored in a sequential order according to a search key",
            "c)\tA hash function is computed on some attribute and that decides the block",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Heap file organization means that any record can be placed wherever there is space for that record. There is no ordering of records. Typically there is a single file for each relation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "2.\tWhat is sequential file organization?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAny record can be placed wherever there is a space for the record",
            "b)\tRecords are stored in a sequential order according to a search key",
            "c)\tA hash function is computed on some attribute and that decides the block",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sequential file organization means that Records are stored in a sequential order according to a search key. The records are ordered. "
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "3.\tWhat is hashing file organization?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAny record can be placed wherever there is a space for the record",
            "b)\tRecords are stored in a sequential order according to a search key",
            "c)\tA hash function is computed on some attribute and that decides the block",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hashing file organization means that a hash function is computed on some attribute and that decides the block. The result of the hash function specifies which block of the file the record should be placed in. "
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "4.\tWhat is a search key in sequential file organization?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tA number assigned to each record",
            "b)\tNecessarily the primary key",
            "c)\tAny attribute or a set of attributes",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A search key in sequential file organization is any attribute or a set of attributes that need not be a primary key or even a superkey. "
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "5.\tMetadata about the relations are stored in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFile header",
            "b)\tData dictionary",
            "c)\tData query",
            "d)\tData analyser"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A relational schema needs to maintain data about the data called as metadata. Metadata about the relations is stored in the Data dictionary."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "6.\tData dictionary is also called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tData log",
            "b)\tSystem log",
            "c)\tSystem catalog",
            "d)\tSystem database log"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Data dictionary is also called as System Catalog. "
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "7.\tWhat is a multitable clustering file organization?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt stores related records of two or more relations in each block",
            "b)\tIt stores related data about the relations in each block",
            "c)\tIt links each and every block by introducing an external attribute",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A multitable clustering file organization stores the related records of two or more relations in each block. This allows us to read records that satisfy a join condition by using one block read. "
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following need to be stored in the data dictionary?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tName of the relation",
            "b)\tDomains and lengths of attributes",
            "c)\tIntegrity constraints",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Name of the relation, Domains and lengths of attributes and Integrity constraints all must be stored in the data dictionary."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "9.\tThe subsystem responsible for the allocation of buffer space is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBuffer allocator",
            "b)\tBuffer manager",
            "c)\tBuffer enhancer",
            "d)\tBuffer intermediary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The subsystem responsible for the allocation of buffer space is called as buffer manager. Programs on the database make requests to the buffer manager and it in in turn allocates the buffer space. "
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "10.\tWhat is the full form of LRU (in buffer replacement strategy)?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLeast Reactive User",
            "b)\tLeast Recently Used",
            "c)\tLeast Read URL",
            "d)\tLowest Reading User"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The full form of LRU is Least Recently Used. In this, the least recently used program is substituted by the new request. "
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "1.\tThe types of access that are supported efficiently are called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAccess modes",
            "b)\tAccess types",
            "c)\tAccess time",
            "d)\tAccess overhead"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The types of access that are supported efficiently are called as Access types. Access types can include finding records with a specified attribute value or within a particular range."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "2.\tThe time it takes to find a particular data item is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInsertion time",
            "b)\tDeletion time",
            "c)\tTime overhead",
            "d)\tAccess time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The time it takes to find a particular data item or a set of data items using the technique in question is called as access time."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "3.\tThe time it takes to insert a new data item is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInsertion time",
            "b)\tDeletion time",
            "c)\tTime overhead",
            "d)\tAccess time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time it takes to insert a new data item is called Insertion time. This value includes the time taken to find the correct place to insert the new data item as well as the time it takes to update the index structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "4.\tThe time it takes to delete a data item is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInsertion time",
            "b)\tDeletion time",
            "c)\tTime overhead",
            "d)\tAccess time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The time it takes to delete a data item is called as deletion time. This value includes finding the item to be deleted and the time taken to update the index structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "5.\tThe additional space occupied by an index structure is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAccess modes",
            "b)\tSpace types",
            "c)\tAccess time",
            "d)\tSpace overhead"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The additional space occupied by an index structure is called as space overhead. It is usually a worthwhile sacrifice to achieve improved performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "6.\tIf the file containing the records is sequentially ordered, a ___________ is an index whose search key also defines the sequential order of the file.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tClustering data",
            "b)\tCluttering index",
            "c)\tClustering index",
            "d)\tClustering number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the file containing the records is sequentially ordered, a Clustering index is an index whose search key also defines the sequential order of the file. Clustering indices are also called as primary indices but they do not denote an index on the primary key. Such indices can be built on any search key."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "8.\tIf an index entry appears for every search key value in the file, it is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDense key",
            "b)\tDense index",
            "c)\tSparse key",
            "d)\tSparse index"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the file containing the records is sequentially ordered, a Clustering index is an index whose search key also defines the sequential order of the file. Clustering indices are also called as primary indices."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "9.\tIf an index entry appears for only some of the search key values in the file, it is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDense key",
            "b)\tDense index",
            "c)\tSparse key",
            "d)\tSparse index"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a dense index, an index entry appears for every search key value in the file. In a dense clustering index, the index record contains the search-key value and a pointer to the first data record with that search-key value."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "10.\tIndices with two or more levels are called as?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMultiple Indices",
            "b)\tMultilevel indices",
            "c)\tBi- tri- Indices",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a sparse index, an index entry appears for only some of the search key values. Sparse indices can be used only if the relation is stored in the sorted order of the search key i.e. if the index is a clustering index."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "11.\tA search key containing more than one attribute is called a _________ search key",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMultiple",
            "b)\tMultilevel",
            "c)\tComposite",
            "d)\tPrimary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Indices with two or more levels are called as multilevel indices. They require significantly few I/O operations than searching using binary search."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "2.\tWhat are the leaf nodes in a B+ tree?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe topmost nodes",
            "b)\tThe bottommost nodes",
            "c)\tThe nodes in between the top and bottom nodes",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: B+ trees are always balanced. Every path from the root to the leaf of the tree is of the same length. "
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "3.\tNon-leaf nodes are also called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInternal nodes",
            "b)\tExternal nodes",
            "c)\tMiddle nodes",
            "d)\tPrimary nodes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The bottommost nodes that mark the end of a tree are known as the leaf nodes in a B+ tree."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "4.\tThe queries used to find all records with search key values in a particular range are known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGap queries",
            "b)\tGraph queries",
            "c)\tRange queries",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Non leaf nodes are also known as internal nodes. A non-leaf node may hold up to n pointers and should hold at least n/2 pointers. "
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "6.\tIf a relation can have more than one record containing the same search key value, the search key is said to be a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUnique search key",
            "b)\tNon unique search key",
            "c)\tMultiple search key",
            "d)\tIdentical search key"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The queries used to find all records with search key values in a particular range are known as Range queries. These type of queries are executed using procedures. "
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "7.\tState true or false: The fanout of nodes can be increased by using a technique called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPrefix compression",
            "b)\tPostfix compression",
            "c)\tPrefix expansion",
            "d)\tPostfix expansion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Both insertion and deletion of records might require the change in position of the initial nodes because the new data value might not exactly fit into the B+ tree. Thus rotation of the nodes is generally required. "
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "8.\tInsertion of a large number of entries at a time into an index is referred to as _______ of the index.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBulk loading",
            "b)\tMass insertion",
            "c)\tQuick insertion",
            "d)\tQuick loading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a relation can have more than one record containing the same search key value, the search key is said to be a non-unique search key. A problem with non-unique search keys is inefficiency during delete operations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "9.\t___________ are the indices that store the values of some attributes along with the pointers to the recor.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBinary indices",
            "b)\tCovering indices",
            "c)\tKey indices",
            "d)\tStatic indices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fanout of nodes can be increased by using a technique called prefix compression. In this, we do not store the entire value of the search key at the node. We only store the prefix of the search key. "
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "1.\tThe term ______ is used to denote a unit of storage that can store one or more records",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBasket",
            "b)\tBucket",
            "c)\tUnit",
            "d)\tSet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The term bucket is used to denote a unit of storage that can store one or more records. A bucket is typically a disk block but it can also be larger than a disk block. "
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "2.\tIf K denotes the set of all the search key values, and B denotes the set of all bucket addresses, a function from K to B is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBucket function",
            "b)\tAddress function",
            "c)\tHash function",
            "d)\tSearch function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If K denotes the set of all the search key values, and B denotes the set of all bucket addresses, a function h from K to B is called as the hash function. It determines which bucket should contain the data in question. "
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "3.\tIn a __________ , we obtain the address of the disk block containing a desired record directly by computing a function on the search key value of the record",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tHash file organization",
            "b)\tHash index organization",
            "c)\tHashing address",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hashing can be used for 2 different purposes, hash file organization and hash index organization. In a Hash file organization, we obtain the address of the disk block containing a desired record directly by computing a function on the search key value of the record. "
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "4.\tIn a __________ we organize the search keys, with their associated pointers, into a hash file structure",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tHash file organization",
            "b)\tHash index organization",
            "c)\tHashing address",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hashing can be used for 2 different purposes, hash file organization and hash index organization. In a hash index organization, we organize the search keys, with their associated pointers, into a hash file structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "5.\tWhat is a bucket overflow?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tWhen a bucket does not have enough space",
            "b)\tThere are insufficient buckets",
            "c)\tWhen Bucket skew occurs",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bucket overflow can occur in many ways. When a bucket does not have enough space, there are insufficient buckets, when a bucket skew occurs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "6.\tSome buckets are assigned more records than the others which causes bucket overflow, this condition is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBucket sufficiency",
            "b)\tBucket insufficiency",
            "c)\tBucket skew",
            "d)\tBucket normalcy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Some buckets are assigned more records than the others which causes bucket overflow, this condition is called as Bucket skew. Skew occurs if multiple records have the same search key or if the given hash function is non uniform. "
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "7.\tOverflow handling using a linked list of buckets is called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBucket chaining",
            "b)\tOverflow chaining",
            "c)\tBucket linking",
            "d)\tOverflow linking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the overflow buckets are chained together in a linked list. Overflow handling using a linked list of buckets is called as Overflow chaining."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich of the following is the worst hash function among the given choices",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe sum of the digits modulo 8",
            "b)\tThe sum of the digits modulo 2",
            "c)\tThe sum of the digits modulo 5",
            "d)\tThe sum of the digits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A hash index organizes the search keys, with their associated pointers, into a hash file structure. We can construct a hash index by applying a hash function on a search key and store the key and its associated pointers in the bucket. "
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "1.\tDynamic hashing allows us to?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAccommodate the growth of the database",
            "b)\tAccommodate the shrinkage of the database",
            "c)\tAllows modification of hash function",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dynamic hashing allows us to accommodate the growth of the database and the shrinkage of the database by allowing us to change the hash function dynamically. "
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "2.\tDynamic hashing is also called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tExtended hashing",
            "b)\tExtendable hashing",
            "c)\tStatic hashing",
            "d)\tMovable hashing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dynamic hashing is also called as extendable hashing because it can accommodate the growth and shrinkage of the database. "
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich of the following operations can be performed on an extendable hash structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLookup",
            "b)\tInsertion",
            "c)\tDeletion",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We can perform lookup, insertion and deletion on a dynamic hash structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "4.\tThe space overhead in dynamic hashing is ________ than that of static hashing",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMore",
            "b)\tLess",
            "c)\tEqual",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The space overhead in dynamic hashing is less than that of static hashing. This is because the hash function is chosen based on the size of the file at some anticipated point in the future. "
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "5.\tWhich of the following is a disadvantage of the dynamic hashing structure",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBuckets can be allocated dynamically",
            "b)\tLookup involves additional level of indirection",
            "c)\tIt involves a lesser space overhead",
            "d)\tHash structure can be modified dynamically"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In dynamic hashing, lookup involves an additional level of indirection. The rest of the options are the advantages of dynamic hashing."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "6.\tThe form of dynamic hashing that avoids the additional level of indirection is called as  _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLinear hashing",
            "b)\tStatic hashing",
            "c)\tDirective hashing",
            "d)\tIndirective hashing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The form of dynamic hashing that avoids the additional level of indirection is called as Linear hashing. This has more overflow buckets than extendable hashing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "7.\tHash structures are not the best choice for which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tA search key on which individual point queries are likely",
            "b)\tA search key which is invalid",
            "c)\tA search key on which range queries are likely",
            "d)\tA search key on which multi-level queries are likely"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hash structures are not the best choice for search keys on which range queries are likely because the range queries might contain different values of the search keys which might result in improper placement in the hash table. "
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following is an issue that needs to be considered while choosing an indexing technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFrequency of insertion and deletion",
            "b)\tData types of the data",
            "c)\tNumber of items in the relation",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frequency of insertion and deletion has to be taken into consideration while choosing an indexing technique. The frequency of insertion and deletion determines the hash index. "
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich of the following hash function classifies data into least number of buckets?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSum of digits modulo 8",
            "b)\tSum of digits modulo 5",
            "c)\tSum of digits modulo 2",
            "d)\tSum of digits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sum of digits modulo 2 classifies the data into only 2 buckets i.e. 0 and 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich of the following hash function classifies data into the highest number of buckets ?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSum of digits modulo 8",
            "b)\tSum of digits modulo 5",
            "c)\tSum of digits modulo 2",
            "d)\tSum of digits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The sum of the digits hash function classifies the data into 10 different buckets thus making it the highest. "
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "1.\tA bitmap is  _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAn array of bits",
            "b)\tAn index of bits",
            "c)\tA function mapping all the bits of data",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A bitmap is simply an array of bits. A bitmap can be used for various purposes such as bitmap indexing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "2.\tA _________ on the attribute A of relation r consists of one bitmap for each value that A can take",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBitmap array",
            "b)\tBitmap index",
            "c)\tBitmap excess",
            "d)\tBitmap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A bitmap index on the attribute A of relation r consists of one bitmap for each value that A can take. Each bitmap contains as many bits as the number of records in the relation."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "3.\tIntersection of the bitmaps is done by",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLogical AND",
            "b)\tLogical OR",
            "c)\tLogical NOT",
            "d)\tLogical NOR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The intersection of the bitmaps is done by the logical AND operation. This is similar to the binary set intersection operation which is done by the logical AND operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "4.\tWhat does an existence bitmap do?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt recognizes deleted records",
            "b)\tIt inserts values into empty bitmaps",
            "c)\tIt makes sure that no records are deleted",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An existence bitmap is used to recognize deleted records and not to prevent deletion of records. It also does not insert any records into empty bitmaps. "
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "5.\tThe complement operation in bitmaps is done by using",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLogical AND",
            "b)\tLogical OR",
            "c)\tLogical NOT",
            "d)\tLogical NOR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The complement operation in bitmaps is done by using the logical not operator. This is similar to the binary complement operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "7.\tWe create an index in SQL using _______ command",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCreate index",
            "b)\tNew index",
            "c)\tCreate new index",
            "d)\tDevelop index"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bitmaps can be combined with B+ trees for relations where a few attribute values are extremely common. "
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "8.\tWe delete and index in SQL using the ________ command",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRemove index",
            "b)\tDelete index",
            "c)\tDrop index",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We create an index in SQL using the create index command. Eg: create index dept_index on instructor(dept_name). "
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich of the following operations is used for the union of bitmaps?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLogical AND",
            "b)\tLogical OR",
            "c)\tLogical NOT",
            "d)\tLogical NOR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We delete and index in SQL using the drop index command. Syntax: drop index ;"
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following are steps in query processing?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tParsing and translation",
            "b)\tOptimization",
            "c)\tEvaluation",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Parsing and translation, optimization, evaluation are all the basic steps to process a query. "
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "2.\tA relational algebra operation annotated with instructions on how to evaluate it is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tEvaluation algebra",
            "b)\tEvaluation plan",
            "c)\tEvaluation primitive",
            "d)\tEvaluation engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  A relational algebra operation annotated with instructions on how to evaluate it is called Evaluation primitive. The evaluation primitive is the basis for evaluation of queries. "
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "3.\tA sequence of primitive operations that can be used to evaluate a query are called as  __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tQuery evaluation algebra",
            "b)\tQuery evaluation plan",
            "c)\tQuery evaluation primitive",
            "d)\tQuery evaluation engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A sequence of primitive operations that can be used to evaluate a query are called as Query evaluation plan. This is used by the query evaluation engine to process the queries. "
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "4.\tThe lowest level operator to access data in query processing is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFile scan",
            "b)\tFile manipulation",
            "c)\tFile handling",
            "d)\tFile organization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lowest level operator to access data in query processing is file scan. File scans are algorithms that locate and retrieve records that fulfill a selection criterion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "5.\tSearch algorithms that use an index are referred to as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIndex scans",
            "b)\tSearch scans",
            "c)\tPrimary scans",
            "d)\tEquality scans"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Search algorithms that use an index are called as index scans. We use the selection predicate to guide us through the choice of index to use in processing the query. "
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "6.\tSorting of relations that do not fit in memory is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInternal sorting",
            "b)\tExternal sorting",
            "c)\tOverflow sorting",
            "d)\tOverload sorting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sorting of relations that do not fit in memory is called as external sorting."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "7.\tA selection of the form satisfying the intersection of all records satisfying individual simple conditions is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConjunctive selection",
            "b)\tDisjunctive selection",
            "c)\tNegation",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A selection of the form satisfying the intersection of all records satisfying individual simple conditions is a conjunctive selection. This is a form of complex selection predicate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "8.\tA selection of the form satisfying the union of all records satisfying individual simple conditions is",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConjunctive selection",
            "b)\tDisjunctive selection",
            "c)\tNegation",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A selection of the form satisfying the intersection of all records satisfying individual simple conditions is a disjunctive selection. This is a form of complex selection predicate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "9.\tA selection of the form giving all the records not satisfying simple individual conditions is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConjunctive selection",
            "b)\tDisjunctive selection",
            "c)\tNegation",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A selection of the form giving all the records not satisfying simple individual conditions is negation. This is a form of complex selection predicate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich of the following can be implemented?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConjunctive selection using one index",
            "b)\tConjunctive selection using composite index",
            "c)\tConjunctive selection by intersection of identifiers",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Conjunctive selection using one index, conjunctive selection using composite index and conjunctive selection by intersection of identifiers can be implemented. These are A7, A8, A9 algorithms that use an index. "
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "1.\tA join of the form r ⨝r.A=s.B s is called as",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tEqui join",
            "b)\tLeft outer join",
            "c)\tRight outer join",
            "d)\tFull outer join"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A join of the form r ⨝r.A=s.B s is called as equi-join where A and B are sets of attributes of r and s respectively. "
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "What type of join is this?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tEqui join",
            "b)\tHash join",
            "c)\tNested loop join",
            "d)\tBlock nested loop join"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The given algorithm is called as a nested loop join because it basically consists of two nested for loops in it i.e. one for loop is inside another for loop. "
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "3.\tIf nested loop join is done on a per block basis rather than on a per tuple basis, it is called as",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tEqui join",
            "b)\tHash join",
            "c)\tNested loop join",
            "d)\tBlock nested loop join"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If nested loop join is done on a per block basis rather than on a per tuple basis, it is called as Block nested loop join. Within each pair of blocks, every tuple in one block is paired with every tuple in the other block to generate all possible combinations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "4.\tThe merge join can be used to compute",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tNatural joins",
            "b)\tEqui joins",
            "c)\tBoth the mentioned",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The merge join can be used to compute both equijoins and natural joins. This is also called as the sort-merge-join algorithm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "5.\tThe ___________ merges the sorted relation with leaf entries of the secondary B+ tree index.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMerge join algorithm",
            "b)\tHybrid merge join algorithm",
            "c)\tHash join algorithm",
            "d)\tHybrid Hash join algorithm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Hybrid merge join algorithm merges the sorted relation with leaf entries of the secondary B+ tree index. The result contains tuples from the sorted relation and addresses for tuples from the unsorted relation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "6.\tThe splitting of input until each partition of the build input fits the memory is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTemporary partitioning",
            "b)\tBlock partitioning",
            "c)\tRecursive partitioning",
            "d)\tByte partitioning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The splitting of input until each partition of the build input fits the memory is called as recursive partitioning."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "7.\tOverflow resolution is performed when,",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tA hash index overflow is detected",
            "b)\tExtra hash indices are to be added",
            "c)\tWhen the number of partitions are to be increased",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hash table overflows can be handled by either overflow resolution or overflow avoidance. Overflow resolution is performed when a hash index overflow is detected. "
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following is not a set operation",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUnion",
            "b)\tIntersection",
            "c)\tAnd operation",
            "d)\tSet difference"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The AND operation is not a set operation, it is a logical bit operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich of the following joins preserves the tuples of the relation on the left side of the operator?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLeft outer join",
            "b)\tNatural join",
            "c)\tRight outer join",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Left outer join and full outer join both preserve the tuples on the left side of the operator. "
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "1.\tIf the results of one operation are passed on to the other, it is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tChain",
            "b)\tPipeline",
            "c)\tMaterialized",
            "d)\tTree"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the results of one operation are passed on to the other, it is called as Pipelined. This can be used to evaluate several expressions simultaneously. "
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "2.\tThe result of each intermediate operation are created and then are used for valuation of the next level operations, this evaluation is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tChain evaluation",
            "b)\tPipeline evaluation",
            "c)\tMaterialized evaluation",
            "d)\tDemand driven evaluation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The result of each intermediate operation are created and then are used foe valuation of the next level operations, this evaluation is called as Materialized evaluation. This is not space effective as we need to construct the temporary relations which must be written to a disk. "
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "3.\tIf the system makes repeated requests for tuples from the operation at the top of the table, it is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDemand driven pipeline",
            "b)\tProducer driven pipeline",
            "c)\tQuery driven pipeline",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the system makes repeated requests for tuples from the operation at the top of the table, it is called as demand driven pipeline. Each time an operation receives a request for tuples, it computes the next tuple or tuples to be returned and then returns that tuple. "
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "4.\tIf the operations do not wait to produce tuples, then it is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDemand driven pipeline",
            "b)\tProducer driven pipeline",
            "c)\tQuery driven pipeline",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the operations do not wait to produce tuples, then it is called as producer driven pipeline. IT does not wait to produce tuples but it produces tuples eagerly. "
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "7.\tWhich of the following techniques does not exist?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPipelined join technique",
            "b)\tLeft pipelined join technique",
            "c)\tRight pipelined join technique",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sorting is an inherently blocking operation i.e. output is not given until all the tuples from their input are examined"
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "9.\tThe usage of two buffers, with one continuing execution of the algorithm while the other is written is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDouble execution",
            "b)\tMulti tasking",
            "c)\tDouble buffering",
            "d)\tDouble algorithm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Join is not an inherently blocking algorithm. This is because all the tuples need not be examined to execute the join operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich of the following functions does an iterator not provide",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOpen()",
            "b)\tNext()",
            "c)\tClose()",
            "d)\tWait()"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pipelined join technique, both left and right are evaluation techniques that can be used to organize data. "
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "1.\tIf on every legal database instant, the two expressions generate the same set of tuples, the expressions are called as",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tEqual",
            "b)\tEquivalent",
            "c)\tSimilar",
            "d)\tIdentical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If on every legal database instant, the two expressions generate the same set of tuples, the expressions are called as Equivalent relational algebra expressions. The order of the tuples is completely irrelevant for equivalency. "
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich of the following operations are associative",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tNatural joins",
            "b)\tTheta joins",
            "c)\tBoth the mentioned",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Selection operations are commutative i.e. selection1(selection2(R)) = selection2(selection1(R)). "
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "4.\tWhich of the following set operations is not commutative?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUnion",
            "b)\tIntersection",
            "c)\tSet difference",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both natural join operation and theta join operation are associative. The commutativity and associativity of the join operations are important for join reordering in query optimization. "
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "6.\tIf no rule can be derived from any combination of others then the set of rules is said to be ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPrimitive",
            "b)\tAxiomatic",
            "c)\tMinimal",
            "d)\tAtomic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The set difference operation is not commutative. As the position of the set difference operator affects the result of the operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "7.\tTheta join operations are",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCommutative",
            "b)\tAssociative",
            "c)\tDistributive under projection",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The projection operation distributes over the union operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following operations is associative",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSet union",
            "b)\tSet intersection",
            "c)\tSet difference",
            "d)\tTheta join"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A set of equivalence rules is said to be minimal if no rule can be derived from any combination of others. Query optimizers use minimal sets of equivalence rules. "
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich of the following set operations does the selection operation distribute over?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUnion",
            "b)\tIntersection",
            "c)\tDifference",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The theta join operations are commutative, associative and are distributive under projection. "
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following information does the database system catalog store?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tNumber of tuples",
            "b)\tNumber of blocks",
            "c)\tSize of a tuple of a relation",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The database system catalog stores the number of tuples, number of blocks, size of a tuple in a relation and the blocking factor in it as statistical data."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "2.\tMost databases store the distribution of values for each attribute as a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tHistogram",
            "b)\tPie chart",
            "c)\tLine graph",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Most of the databases store the distribution of values for each attribute as a histogram.in which the values for the attributes are divided into various ranges. "
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "3.\tWhat is the function of the equi-width histogram?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAdjusts boundaries of the ranges such that each range has the same number of values",
            "b)\tDivides range of values into equal sized ranges",
            "c)\tDivides the range of values into ideally sized ranges",
            "d)\tDoes not divide the range of values."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The equi width histogram divides the range of values into equal sized ranges."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "4.\tWhat kind of a sample must be used for statistical analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tA random sample",
            "b)\tA sample having excessive representation of a relation",
            "c)\tA sample having suppressive representation of a relation",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A random sample must be taken into consideration for statistical analysis because it gives a fair result on the data analysis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "5.\tThe ________ SQL command generates statistics on a particular relation",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tStatistic",
            "b)\tAnalyze",
            "c)\tModify",
            "d)\tRunstats"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The analyze command is used to generate statistics on a particular set of relations. The runstats command is also valid but not in SQL. It is used in IBM DB2."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "6.\tThe union of all records satisfying the individual simple conditions Oi is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConjunctive selection",
            "b)\tDisjunctive selection",
            "c)\tNegation",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The union of all records satisfying the individual simple conditions Oi is called as disjunctive selection. It is a form of a complex selection. "
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "7.\tThe intersection of all records satisfying the individual simple conditions Oi is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConjunctive selection",
            "b)\tDisjunctive selection",
            "c)\tNegation",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The intersection of all records satisfying the individual simple conditions Oi is called as conjunctive selection. It is a form of a complex selection. "
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "9.\tSize estimation can be done for which of the following processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tProjection",
            "b)\tAggregation",
            "c)\tSet operation",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Estimation of the result of a join is possible and can be done using the Cartesian product and intersections of the two relations. It is more complicated than estimating size of a selection. "
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "10.\tThe size of a _____ is simply V(A,r) where r is the relation and A is a distinct value",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tProjection",
            "b)\tOuter join",
            "c)\tAggregation",
            "d)\tInner join"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Size estimation can be done for projection, aggregation, set operations, join operations and also the selection operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "1.\tA ________ explores the space of all query evaluation plans that are equivalent to a given query.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCost based optimizer",
            "b)\tSpace based optimizer",
            "c)\tTime based optimizer",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A cost based optimizer explores the space of all query evaluation plans that are equivalent to a given query, and chooses the one with the least estimated cost. "
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "2.\tWhat is the disadvantage of cost based optimizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIt is too expensive",
            "b)\tIt is inefficient in producing results",
            "c)\tIt does not perform the desired function",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cost based optimizers may be expensive as exploring space of all possible plans might prove to be costly. "
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "3.\tA particular sort order is said to be _________ sort order if it could be useful for a later operation.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tInteresting",
            "b)\tReusable",
            "c)\tEfficient",
            "d)\tGood"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A particular sort order is said to be interesting-sort order if it could be useful for a later operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "4.\tThe rule that allows transformation of a logical operation to a physical operation is called",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLogical equivalence rule",
            "b)\tPhysical equivalence rule",
            "c)\tMemory equivalence rule",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rule that allows transformation of a logical operation to a physical operation is called as a physical equivalence rule. It is a new class of equivalence rules. "
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "6.\tOptimizers use __________ to reduce the cost of optimization.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAnalyzers",
            "b)\tStatistics",
            "c)\tHeuristics",
            "d)\tCaches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For promoting space efficiency, making multiple copies of the same sub-expressions must be avoided. "
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "7.\tThe join orders where the right operand of each join is in one of the initial relations are called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRight deep join orders",
            "b)\tLeft deep join orders",
            "c)\tOuter join orders",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cost based optimizers may be expensive as exploring space of all possible plans might prove to be costly. So, optimizers use heuristics to reduce the cost of optimization. "
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "8.\tCaching and reuse of query plans is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tQuery caching",
            "b)\tPlan caching",
            "c)\tPlan memorizing",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The join orders where the right operand of each join is in one of the initial relations are called as left deep join orders."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "9.\tWhat technique is used for the evaluation of a query with a nested sub query?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCaching",
            "b)\tDecorrelated evaluation",
            "c)\tCorrelated evaluation",
            "d)\tTime based evaluation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Caching and reuse of query plans is called as plan caching. It is used because the optimal plan for the new constants may differ from the optimal plan for the initial values. "
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "10.\tThe process of replacing a nested query with a query with a join is known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCorrelation",
            "b)\tDecorrelation",
            "c)\tCache handling",
            "d)\tJoin replacement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The technique used to evaluate a query with a nested sub query is called as correlated evaluation. It is not very efficient as a large number of I/O operations may occur. "
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "1.\tA view whose contents are computed and stored is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tStorage view",
            "b)\tBackup view",
            "c)\tMaterialized view",
            "d)\tAdvanced view"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A view whose contents are computed and stored is called as a materialized view. I does not only store the query defining the view. "
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "2.\tThe task of keeping a view up to date with the underlying data is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tView handling",
            "b)\tView maintenance",
            "c)\tView management",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The task of keeping a view up to date with the underlying data is called as view maintenance."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "3.\tWhat is incremental materialized view maintenance?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tModifying all the parts of the view",
            "b)\tModifying only the affected parts of the view",
            "c)\tNot modifying the view",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Modifying only the affected parts of the materialized view is called as incremental view maintenance. It is much more efficient than ordinary view management. "
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "4.\tWhich of the following is a type of materialized view management?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIncremental view management",
            "b)\tImmediate view management",
            "c)\tDeferred view management",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Incremental, immediate and deferred are all different types of materialized view management techniques. Most database systems perform immediate view management. "
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "5.\tWhat are differentials in view management?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe differences between relations",
            "b)\tThe changes made to a relation",
            "c)\tThe  changes made to an expression",
            "d)\tMore than one of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The changes made to a relation or and expression are known as differentials in materialized view management."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "6.\tThe sequence of queries that reflect the typical load on the system are known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tEfficacies",
            "b)\tWorkload",
            "c)\tSelection",
            "d)\tBalancers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sequence of queries that reflect the typical workload on the system are known as workload.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "7.\tThe problem of an update affecting the execution of a query associated with the update is known as the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUpdation problem",
            "b)\tIncremental problem",
            "c)\tHalloween problem",
            "d)\tOptimization problem"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The problem of an update affecting the execution of a query associated with the update is known as the Halloween problem. This was because it was first recognized on the Halloween day at IBM. "
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "8.\tReducing the complexity of complex queries by similarly handling sub-queries is known as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tComplex query handling",
            "b)\tMulti query optimization",
            "c)\tComplex query optimization",
            "d)\tParametric query optimization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reducing the complexity of complex queries by similarly handling sub-queries is known as multi query optimization. "
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich of the following is a multi-query optimization technique",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tShared scan optimization",
            "b)\tParametric query optimization",
            "c)\tIndex optimization",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shared scan optimization is a multi query optimization technique. "
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "10.\tIf a query is optimized without providing specific values for its parameters the technique is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tComplex query handling",
            "b)\tMulti query optimization",
            "c)\tComplex query optimization",
            "d)\tParametric query optimization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If a query is optimized without providing specific values for its parameters the technique is called parametric query optimization. "
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "1.\tCollections of operations that form a single logical unit of work are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tViews",
            "b)\tNetworks",
            "c)\tUnits",
            "d)\tTransactions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Collections of operations that form a single logical unit of work are called transactions. A database system must ensure proper execution of transactions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "2.\tThe “all-or-none” property is commonly referred to as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIsolation",
            "b)\tDurability",
            "c)\tAtomicity",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The all or none policy is commonly referred to as atomicity. It ensures that a work is either completed or not completed and there are no intermediate stages. "
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich of the following is a property of transactions?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAtomicity",
            "b)\tDurability",
            "c)\tIsolation",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Atomicity, Durability and Isolation are all properties of transactions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "4.\tExecution of translation in isolation preserves the _________ of a database",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAtomicity",
            "b)\tConsistency",
            "c)\tDurability",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Execution of translation in isolation preserves the consistency of a database. It ensures that no other transaction is running concurrently. "
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "5.\tWhich of the following is not a property of a transaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAtomicity",
            "b)\tSimplicity",
            "c)\tIsolation",
            "d)\tDurability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Simplicity is not a property of a transaction. Atomicity, Isolation, Durability are all parts of ACID properties. "
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "6.\tWhich of the following systems is responsible for ensuring durability?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRecovery system",
            "b)\tAtomic system",
            "c)\tConcurrency control system",
            "d)\tCompiler system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The recovery system is responsible for the maintenance of durability. In addition, it also ensures atomicity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "7.\tWhich of the following systems is responsible for ensuring isolation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRecovery system",
            "b)\tAtomic system",
            "c)\tConcurrency control system",
            "d)\tCompiler system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The concurrency control system is responsible for ensuring isolation in a database system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "9.\tA transaction that has not been completed successfully is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCompensating transaction",
            "b)\tAborted transaction",
            "c)\tActive transaction",
            "d)\tPartially committed transaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Information residing in the volatile storage does not usually survive system crashes but the information in stable storage can survive system crashes efficiently. "
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich of the following is not a transaction state?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tActive",
            "b)\tPartially committed",
            "c)\tFailed",
            "d)\tCompensated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Aborted transaction is a state after the transaction has been rolled back and the database has been restored to the state prior to the transaction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "11.\tThe execution sequences in concurrency control are termed as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSerials",
            "b)\tSchedules",
            "c)\tOrganizations",
            "d)\tTime tables"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Compensated is not a transaction state. But active, partially committed and failed are different states of a transaction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "12.\tThe scheme that controls the interaction between executing transactions is called as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConcurrency control scheme",
            "b)\tMultiprogramming scheme",
            "c)\tSerialization scheme",
            "d)\tSchedule scheme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The execution sequences in concurrency control are known as schedules. "
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "1.\tI and J are _________ if they are operations by different transactions on the same data item, and at least one of them is a write operation.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConflicting",
            "b)\tOverwriting",
            "c)\tIsolated",
            "d)\tDurable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: I and J are conflicting if they are operations by different transactions on the same data item, and at least one of them is a write operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "2.\tIf a schedule S can be transformed into a schedule S’ by a series of swaps of non-conflicting instructions, then S and S’ are",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tNon conflict equivalent",
            "b)\tEqual",
            "c)\tConflict equivalent",
            "d)\tIsolation equivalent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If a schedule S can be transformed into a schedule S’ by a series of swaps of non-conflicting instructions, then S and S’ are conflict equivalent. Not all serial schedules are conflict equivalent to each other. "
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "3.\tA schedule is __________ if it is conflict equivalent to a serial schedule.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConflict serializable",
            "b)\tConflicting",
            "c)\tNon serializable",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A schedule is conflict serializable if it is conflict equivalent to a serial schedule. The concept of conflict equivalence leads to the concept. "
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "4.\tThe set of ________ in a precedence graph consists of all the transactions participating in the schedule",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tVertices",
            "b)\tEdges",
            "c)\tDirections",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The set of vertices in a precedence graph consists of all the transactions participating in the schedule. Precedence graph is a simple and efficient way of determining conflict serializability of the schedule. "
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "5.\tA ___________of the transactions can be obtained by finding a linear order consistent with the partial order of the precedence graph.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSerializability order",
            "b)\tDirection graph",
            "c)\tPrecedence graph",
            "d)\tScheduling scheme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A Serializability order of the transactions can be obtained by finding a linear order consistent with the partial order of the precedence graph. This process is called as topological sorting."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following is the most expensive method?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTimestamping",
            "b)\tPlain locking",
            "c)\tPredicate locking",
            "d)\tSnapshot isolation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If I = read(Q) and J = read(Q) then the order of I and J does not matter because both I  and J are read operations on the query. "
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "1.\tA transaction that performs only one operation is called as a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPartial schedule",
            "b)\tComplete schedule",
            "c)\tDependent schedule",
            "d)\tIndependent schedule"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A transaction that performs only one operation is called as a partial schedule because we don’t include commit or rollback operations on them. "
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "2.\tThe phenomenon in which one failure leads to a series of transaction rollbacks is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCascading rollback",
            "b)\tCascadeless rollback",
            "c)\tCascade cause",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The phenomenon in which one failure leads to a series of transaction rollbacks is called as cascading rollback. B=It is named so because one failure causes the rollback of several other transactions serially."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "4.\tA ___________ is one where, for each pair of transactions Ti and Tj such that Tj reads a data item previously written by Ti , the commit operation of Ti appears before the commit operation of Tj",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPartial schedule",
            "b)\tDependent schedule",
            "c)\tRecoverable schedule",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Every cascadeless schedule is also recoverable because in a cascadeless schedule, the commit operations occur in the same sequence as that of write and read operations of two transactions respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "6.\tWhich of the following are the advantages of transaction concurrency?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIncreased throughput",
            "b)\tIncreased utilization",
            "c)\tReduces average response time",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  A Recoverable schedule is one where, for each pair of transactions Ti and Tj such that Tj reads a data item previously written by Ti , the commit operation of Ti appears before the commit operation of Tj."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "7.\tThe average time for a transaction to be completed after it has been submitted is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMinimum response time",
            "b)\tAverage response time",
            "c)\tAverage reaction time",
            "d)\tMinimum reaction time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transactions are safer run serially but can also be run concurrently."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "8.\tIf a schedule is equivalent to a serial schedule, it is called as a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSerializable schedule",
            "b)\tEquivalent schedule",
            "c)\tCommitted schedule",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Concurrency in transactions allow increased throughput, utilization. They also reduce average response time."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich of the following is not a type of a schedule?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPartial schedule",
            "b)\tDependent schedule",
            "c)\tRecoverable schedule",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The average time for a transaction to be completed after it has been submitted is called as Average response time. This gets decreased when concurrency is used in transactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following is a transaction isolation level as specified by SQL standard?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSerializable",
            "b)\tRepeatable read",
            "c)\tRead committed",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Serializable, repeatable read, read committed and read uncommitted are the four levels of transactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "3.\t________ allows only committed data to be read and further requires that no other transaction is allowed to update it between two reads of a data item by a transaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRead uncommitted",
            "b)\tSerializable",
            "c)\tRepeatable read",
            "d)\tRead committed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Serializable level generally allows only serializable executions but in some special cases, it may also allow non-serializable execution."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "4.\t________ allows only committed data to be read, but does not require repeatable reads",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRead uncommitted",
            "b)\tSerializable",
            "c)\tRepeatable read",
            "d)\tRead committed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Repeatable read allows only committed data to be read and further requires that no other transaction is allowed to update it between two reads of a data item by a transaction. However, the transaction may not be serializable with respect to other transactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "5.\t___________ allows uncommitted data to be read",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRead uncommitted",
            "b)\tSerializable",
            "c)\tRepeatable read",
            "d)\tRead committed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Read committed allows only committed data to be read, but does not require repeatable reads. For instance, between two reads of a data item by the transaction, another transaction may have updated the data item and committed."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "7.\tWhen is a timestamp allotted",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tWhen execution begins",
            "b)\tWhen execution is taking place",
            "c)\tWhen execution is completed",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Real uncommitted allows uncommitted data to be read. It is the lowest isolation level allowed by SQL."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "8.\tIn ___________ isolation each transaction is given its own version of the database",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTimestamp",
            "b)\tSnapshot",
            "c)\tLock based",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All the isolation levels above additionally disallow dirty writes, that is, they Disallow writes to a data item that has already been written by another transaction that has not yet committed or aborted."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "9.\tWhat is the disadvantage of locking?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDoes not control concurrency",
            "b)\tIs not atomic",
            "c)\tIs not durable",
            "d)\tHas a poor degree of concurrency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Timestamp is allotted when execution of a transaction begins."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "1.\tIf a transaction has obtained a __________ lock, it can read but cannot write on the item",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tShared mode",
            "b)\tExclusive mode",
            "c)\tRead only mode",
            "d)\tWrite only mode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If a transaction Ti has obtained a shared-mode lock (denoted by S) on item Q, then Ti can read, but cannot write, Q. "
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "2.\tIf a transaction has obtained a ________ lock, it can both read and write on the item",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tShared mode",
            "b)\tExclusive mode",
            "c)\tRead only mode",
            "d)\tWrite only mode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a transaction has obtained an exclusive mode lock, then it can both read and write on the item on which it in operating. "
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "3.\tA transaction can proceed only after the concurrency control manager ________ the lock to the transaction",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGrants",
            "b)\tRequests",
            "c)\tAllocates",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A transaction can proceed only after the concurrency control manager grants the lock to the transaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "4.\tIf a transaction can be granted a lock on an item immediately in spite of the presence of another mode, then the two modes are said to be ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tConcurrent",
            "b)\tEquivalent",
            "c)\tCompatible",
            "d)\tExecutable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  If a transaction can be granted a lock on an item immediately in spite of the presence of another mode, then the two modes are said to be compatible. "
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "5.\tA transaction is made to wait until all ________ locks held on the item are released",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCompatible",
            "b)\tIncompatible",
            "c)\tConcurrent",
            "d)\tEquivalent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A transaction is made to wait until all compatible locks held on the item are released. This ensures that no other transaction is concurrently accessing the same item."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "7.\tThe situation where no transaction can proceed with normal execution is known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRoad block",
            "b)\tDeadlock",
            "c)\tExecution halt",
            "d)\tAbortion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is not necessarily desirable for a transaction to unlock a data item immediately after its final access because serializability may be violated due to this. "
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "8.\tThe protocol that indicates when a transaction may lock and unlock each of the data items is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLocking protocol",
            "b)\tUnlocking protocol",
            "c)\tGranting protocol",
            "d)\tConflict protocol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The situation where no transaction can proceed with normal execution is known as a deadlock. "
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "9.\tIf a transaction Ti may never make progress, then the transaction is said to be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDeadlocked",
            "b)\tStarved",
            "c)\tCommitted",
            "d)\tRolled back"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The protocol that indicates when a transaction may lock and unlock each of the data items is called as locking protocol. Locking protocols restrict the number of schedules. "
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "10.\tThe two phase locking protocol consists which of the following phases?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGrowing phase",
            "b)\tShrinking phase",
            "c)\tMore than one of the mentioned",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a transaction Ti may never make progress, then the transaction is said to be starved. "
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "11.\tIf a transaction may obtain locks but may not release any locks then it is in _______ phase",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGrowing phase",
            "b)\tShrinking phase",
            "c)\tDeadlock phase",
            "d)\tStarved phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The two phased locking protocol consists of the growing phase and the shrinking phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "12.\tIf a transaction may release locks but may not obtain any locks, it is said to be in ______ phase",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tGrowing phase",
            "b)\tShrinking phase",
            "c)\tDeadlock phase",
            "d)\tStarved phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  If a transaction may obtain locks but may not release any locks then it is in growing phase. Growing phase is a phase in two phased locking protocol."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "1.\tA system is in a _______ state if there exists a set of transactions in which every transaction is waiting for another transaction in the set.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDeadlock",
            "b)\tStarved",
            "c)\tIsolated",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A system is in a deadlock state if there exists a set of transactions in which every transaction is waiting for another transaction in the set."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "2.\tWhich of the following is not a method in deadlock handling",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDeadlock prevention",
            "b)\tDeadlock detection",
            "c)\tDeadlock recovery",
            "d)\tDeadlock distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Deadlock distribution is not a method in deadlock handling whereas, deadlock prevention is followed by deadlock detection and deadlock recovery."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "3.\tDeadlocks can be prevented using",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPreemption and transaction rollbacks",
            "b)\tWait and die scheme",
            "c)\tWound-wait scheme",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Preemption and transaction rollbacks, wait and die scheme, wound wait scheme are all different methods of deadlock prevention."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "5.\tLock timeouts have which of the following advantages?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUnnecessary rollbacks do not occur",
            "b)\tTransactions do not starve",
            "c)\tIt is easy to implement",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The wait-die scheme is a non-preemptive technique. When transaction Ti requests a data item currently held by Tj , Ti is allowed to wait only if it has a timestamp smaller than that of Tj (that is, Ti is older than Tj ). Otherwise, Ti is rolled back (dies)."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "6.\tThe _________ graph describes deadlocks precisely",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tWound wait graph",
            "b)\tWait die graph",
            "c)\tWait for graph",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In lock timeout method, unnecessary rollbacks do not occur, transactions do not starve and it is also easy to implement and is hence widely used if transactions are short and long waits are likely to be due to deadlocks."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "7.\tHow do we generally recover from a deadlock?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBy aborting all the transactions",
            "b)\tBy rolling back all the transactions",
            "c)\tBy rolling back only a selected number of transactions",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The wait for graph describes deadlocks precisely. Existence of a cycle in this graph implies that a deadlock will occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "9.\tWhich of the following steps must be taken while choosing a victim?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tAvoiding starvation",
            "b)\tNumber of transactions involved in rollback",
            "c)\tData items used by the transaction",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We generally recover from deadlocks by rolling back only a selected number of transactions"
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following cannot be used to implement a timestamp",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSystem clock",
            "b)\tLogical counter",
            "c)\tExternal time counter",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An external time counter cannot be used to implement a timestamp. System clock and a logical counter can be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "2.\tA logical counter is _________ after a new timestamp has been assigned",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tIncremented",
            "b)\tDecremented",
            "c)\tDoubled",
            "d)\tRemains the same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A logical counter is incremented after a new timestamp has been assigned everytime."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "3.\tW-timestamp(Q) denotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe largest timestamp of any transaction that can execute write(Q) successfully",
            "b)\tThe largest timestamp of any transaction that can execute read(Q) successfully",
            "c)\tThe smallest timestamp of any transaction that can execute write(Q) successfully",
            "d)\tThe smallest timestamp of any transaction that can execute read(Q) successfully"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: W-timestamp(Q) denotes The largest timestamp of any transaction that can execute write(Q) successfully."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "4.\tR-timestamp(Q) denotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe largest timestamp of any transaction that can execute write(Q) successfully",
            "b)\tThe largest timestamp of any transaction that can execute read(Q) successfully",
            "c)\tThe smallest timestamp of any transaction that can execute write(Q) successfully",
            "d)\tThe smallest timestamp of any transaction that can execute read(Q) successfully"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: R-timestamp(Q) denoted the largest timestamp of any transaction that can execute read(Q) successfully."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "5.\tA ________ ensures that any conflicting read and write operations are executed in timestamp order",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tOrganizational protocol",
            "b)\tTimestamp ordering protocol",
            "c)\tTimestamp execution protocol",
            "d)\t802-11 protocol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A timestamp ordering protocol ensures that any conflicting read and write operations are executed in timestamp order."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "6.\tThe default timestamp ordering protocol generates schedules that are",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRecoverable",
            "b)\tNon-recoverable",
            "c)\tStarving",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The timestamp ordering protocol generates schedules that are non-recoverable. But it can be extended to make the schedules recoverable."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following timestamp based protocols generates serializable schedules?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThomas write rule",
            "b)\tTimestamp ordering protocol",
            "c)\tValidation protocol",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Thomas write rule has a greater potential concurrency than the timestamp ordering protocol. This is because it is a modified version of the timestamp ordering protocol in which obsolete write operations can be ignored under certain circumstances."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "9.\tIn timestamp ordering protocol, suppose that the transaction Ti issues read(Q) and TS(Ti)<W-timestamp(Q), then",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRead operation is executed",
            "b)\tRead operation is rejected",
            "c)\tWrite operation is executed",
            "d)\tWrite operation is rejected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thomas write rule protocol generates serializable schedules that no other protocol can generate."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "10.\tIn timestamp ordering protocol, suppose that the transaction Ti issues write(Q) and TS(Ti)<W-timestamp(Q), then",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRead operation is executed",
            "b)\tRead operation is rejected",
            "c)\tWrite operation is executed",
            "d)\tWrite operation is rejected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Suppose that transaction Ti issues read(Q). If TS(Ti ) < W-timestamp(Q), then Ti needs to read a value of Q that was already overwritten. Hence, the read operation is rejected, and Ti is rolled back."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "1.\tThe _________ requires each transaction executes in two or three different phases in its lifetime",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tValidation protocol",
            "b)\tTimestamp protocol",
            "c)\tDeadlock protocol",
            "d)\tView protocol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The validation protocol requires each transaction to execute in two or three different phases in its lifetime depending on whether it is a read only or an update transaction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "2.\tDuring __________ phase, the system reads data and stores them in variables local to the transaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRead phase",
            "b)\tValidation phase",
            "c)\tWrite phase",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During the read phase, the system reads data and stores them in variables local to the transaction. It performs all write operations on temporary local variables without updates on the actual database. "
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "3.\tDuring the _________ phase the validation test is applied to the transaction",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRead phase",
            "b)\tValidation phase",
            "c)\tWrite phase",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the validation phase, the validation test is applied to the transaction. This determines whether the transaction is allowed to proceed or not without causing a violation of serializability. "
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "4.\tDuring the _______ phase, the local variables that hold the write operations are copied to the database",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRead phase",
            "b)\tValidation phase",
            "c)\tWrite phase",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During the write phase, the local variables that hold the write operations are copied to the database. Read only operations omit this phase. "
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "5.\tRead only operations omit the _______ phase",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRead phase",
            "b)\tValidation phase",
            "c)\tWrite phase",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Read only operations do not allow write operation to be performed on them. So, they omit the write phase but execute the read and validation phases. "
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "6.\tWhich of the following timestamp is used to record the time at which the transaction started execution?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tStart(i)",
            "b)\tValidation(i)",
            "c)\tFinish(i)",
            "d)\tWrite(i)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are three different timestamps for each transaction start(i), validation(i), finish(i). Start(i) is used to record the time at which the transaction execution started."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "7.\tWhich of the following timestamps is used to record the time when a transaction has finished its read phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tStart(i)",
            "b)\tValidation(i)",
            "c)\tFinish(i)",
            "d)\tWrite(i)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are three different timestamps for each transaction start(i), validation(i), finish(i). The validation phase is used to record the time at which a transaction has finished its read phase and has started its validation phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following timestamps is used to record the time when a database has completed its write operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tStart(i)",
            "b)\tValidation(i)",
            "c)\tFinish(i)",
            "d)\tWrite(i)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are three different timestamps for each transaction start(i), validation(i), finish(i). Finish(i) is used to record the time when a transaction has finished its write phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "1.\tIn _______ schemes, each write operation creates a new version of Q",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMultiversion",
            "b)\tSnapshot isolation",
            "c)\tLock based",
            "d)\tTimestamp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In multiversion schemes, each write operation creates a new version of Q. When a transaction issues a read operation, the concurrency control manager selects one of the versions of Q to be read. "
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "2.\tIf the first update is overwritten by a second, it is called as a _______ update",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tUseful",
            "b)\tOverlapping",
            "c)\tLost",
            "d)\tConcurrent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the first update is overwritten by a second, it is called as a lost update. This generally occurs whenever two transactions are allowed to write on the database. "
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "4.\tWhich of the following is a variant of snapshot isolation",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFirst committer wins",
            "b)\tFirst updater wins",
            "c)\tMore than one of the mentioned",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Snapshot isolation prevents lost updates because it does not allow two transactions to simultaneously write on the same database. "
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "5.\tUnder ________ the system uses locking mechanism that applies only to updates",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tFirst updater wins",
            "b)\tFirst committer wins",
            "c)\tFirst writer wins",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: First committer wins and first updater wins are two different variations of snapshot isolation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "6.\tThe situation in which each pair of transactions has read a data written by the other, but there is no data written by the transactions is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDeadlock",
            "b)\tRead skew",
            "c)\tDeadlock skew",
            "d)\tWrite skew"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Under first updater wins, the system uses a locking mechanism that applies only to updates. Read operations do not get affected by this mechanism. "
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "7.\tOracle uses __________ for the serializable isolation level",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMultiversion scheme",
            "b)\tTimestamp protocol",
            "c)\tLock based protocol",
            "d)\tSnapshot isolation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The situation in which each pair of transactions has read a data written by the other, but there is no data written by the transactions is called as write skew."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "9.\tIn ________ no two aborts occur unless two concurrent transactions update the same data item.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tMultiversion scheme",
            "b)\tTimestamp protocol",
            "c)\tLock based protocol",
            "d)\tSnapshot isolation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Oracle uses snapshot isolation for the serializable isolation level. PostgreSQL also uses only snapshot isolation for the serializable isolation level. "
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "10.\tWhich of the following transactions can multiversion two phase locking protocol not differentiate.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tRead only transactions",
            "b)\tUpdate transactions",
            "c)\tAll of the mentioned",
            "d)\tDouble operator transactions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Snapshot isolation is attractive in practice because it has a relatively very low overhead. "
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "1.\t________ deletes a data item from a database",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDelete(Q)",
            "b)\tInsert(Q)",
            "c)\tDrop(Q)",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Delete(Q) deletes a data item from a database. Insert(Q) inserts a new data item Q into the database and assign Q an initial value. "
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "2.\tWhich of the following does not lock the entire index",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPhantom locking",
            "b)\tPhantom problem",
            "c)\tIndex locking",
            "d)\tIndex problem"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Index locking avoids locking the entire index. Any transaction that inserts a tuple into a relation must insert information into every index maintained on the relation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich of the following is included in the operational mechanism of the index locking protocol?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tEvery transaction must have at least one index",
            "b)\tA transaction that performs a lookup must acquire a shared lock on all the index leaf nodes that it accesses",
            "c)\tThe rule of the two phase locking mechanism must be observed",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The operational mechanism of the index locking protocol includes, every transaction must have at least one index. A transaction that performs lookup must acquire a shared lock on all the index leaf nodes that it accesses. The rule of the two phase locking mechanism must be followed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "4.\t_________ is a form of two degree consistency designed for programs that iterate over tuples of a relation by using cursors.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tCursor stability",
            "b)\tSerializability",
            "c)\tNon-serializability",
            "d)\tPredicate locking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cursor stability is a form of two degree consistency designed for programs that iterate over tuples of a relation by using cursors. It ensures that the tuple that is currently being processed is locked in shared mode and any modified tuples are locked in exclusive mode until the transaction commits. "
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "5.\tTransactions that involve user interactions are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tValidations",
            "b)\tConversations",
            "c)\tInterfaces",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transactions that involve user interactions are called as conversation. These are named differently to differentiate them from regular transactions. Validation using version numbers is very useful for such transactions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "7.\tTo prevent the phantom phenomenon, _______ is used",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tKey value locking",
            "b)\tNext key locking",
            "c)\tPrevious key locking",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Key value locking provides increased concurrency. Using key value improperly however might cause phantom phenomenon to occur. "
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "8.\tWhich of the following does cursor stability ensure",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tThe tuple that is currently being processed by the iteration is locked in shared mode",
            "b)\tThe tuple that is currently being processed is not locked in shared mode",
            "c)\tAny modified tuples are not locked in exclusive mode",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The failure of a system to prevent a non serialized tuple when two transactions conflict with each other is called as phantom phenomenon. To prevent the phantom phenomenon, the next key locking is used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "1.\tWhich of the following can cause a transaction failure",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLogical error",
            "b)\tSystem error",
            "c)\tMore than one of the mentioned",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Logical errors and system errors are the two types of errors that can generally cause transaction failures. "
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "2.\tIf the transaction can no longer continue with its normal execution because of some internal condition, it is called as a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLogical error",
            "b)\tSystem error",
            "c)\tSystem crash",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the transaction can no longer continue with its normal execution because of some internal condition, it is called as a logical error such as bad input, data not found, overflow or resource limit exceeded. "
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "3.\tIf a system has entered and undesirable state due to which it is unable to continue with normal execution, it is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLogical error",
            "b)\tSystem error",
            "c)\tSystem crash",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a system has entered and undesirable state due to which it is unable to continue with normal execution, it is called as a system error. The transaction however can be re-executed at a later time. "
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "4.\tIf there is a hardware malfunction or a bug in the database that causes the loss of content of volatile storage, it is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLogical error",
            "b)\tSystem error",
            "c)\tSystem crash",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If there is a hardware malfunction or a bug in the database that causes the loss of content of volatile storage, it is called as a system crash. The data in the non-volatile storage remains intact and it is not corrupted. "
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "5.\tThe assumption that the hardware errors bring the system to a halt is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tHalter assumption",
            "b)\tPhantom assumption",
            "c)\tFail-stop assumption",
            "d)\tDisk failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The assumption that the hardware errors bring the system to a halt is called as fail-stop assumption. Well-designed systems have numerous internal checks that bring a system to a halt whenever there is an error. Hence, the fail stop assumption is a reasonable one. "
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "6.\tWhich of the following is not a classification of storage",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tVolatile storage",
            "b)\tNonvolatile storage",
            "c)\tStable storage",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Volatile storage, non-volatile storage and stable storage are three different classifications of storage. Volatile storage is the least secure whereas stable storage is the most secure among them. "
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "7.\tIf a failure has occurred in the midst of a transfer, it is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSuccessful completion",
            "b)\tPartial failure",
            "c)\tTotal failure",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a failure has occurred in the midst of a transfer, it is called as partial failure. After a partial failure, the destination has incorrect information. "
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "9.\tThe partitions of the database into fixed length storage units are called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBlocks",
            "b)\tTuples",
            "c)\tRelations",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of total failure, the failure occurs sufficiently early during the transfer that the destination block remains intact. Thus there is no corruption of data at the destination. "
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "10.\tThe blocks residing on the disk are referred to as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tPhysical blocks",
            "b)\tBuffer blocks",
            "c)\tDisk blocks",
            "d)\tDisk buffer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The database is partitioned into fixed length storage units called as blocks. Blocks are the units of data transfer and may contain several data items. "
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "11.\tThe area of memory where blocks temporarily reside is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tBlock buffer",
            "b)\tDisk buffer",
            "c)\tPhysical buffer",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The blocks residing on the disk are referred to as physical blocks. The blocks residing temporarily in the main memory are referred to as buffer blocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "1.\tThe most widely used structure for recording database modification is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLog",
            "b)\tList",
            "c)\tQueue",
            "d)\tStack"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most widely used structure for recording database modification is called as a log. The log is a sequence of log records recording all the update activities in the database. "
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "2.\tAn update log record describes a ________ database write",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tSingle",
            "b)\tDouble",
            "c)\tTriple",
            "d)\tQuadruple"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An update log record describes a single database write. It has four fields in it which are, transaction identifier, data-item identifier, old value, new value. "
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "3.\tWhich of the following fields does the update log record have?",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTransaction identifier",
            "b)\tData-item identifier",
            "c)\tOld value",
            "d)\tAll of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An update log record describes a single database write. It has four fields in it. The update log record has a transaction identifier, data-item identifier, old value, new value. "
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "4.\tThe unique identifier of the transaction that performed the write operation is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTransaction identifier",
            "b)\tData-item identifier",
            "c)\tOld value",
            "d)\tNew value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The unique identifier of the transaction that performed the write operation is called as transaction identifier. This is a field in the update log record. "
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "5.\tThe value of the data item prior to the write is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTransaction identifier",
            "b)\tData-item identifier",
            "c)\tOld value",
            "d)\tNew value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of the data item prior to the write is called as old value. This is stored in the update log record. "
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "6.\tIf a transaction does not modify the database until it has committed it is said to use a  _______ modification technique",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDeferred",
            "b)\tImmediate",
            "c)\tMore than one of the mentioned",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  If a transaction does not modify the database until it has committed it is said to use a deferred modification technique. Deferred modification has the overhead that transactions need to make local copies of all updated data items. "
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "7.\tWe say that a transaction has been ________ when its commit log record has been output to stable storage.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tLocked",
            "b)\tCompleted",
            "c)\tCommitted",
            "d)\tReleased"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We say that a transaction has been committed when its commit log record has been output to stable storage. At that point, all the earlier records have already been output to stable storage. "
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "9.\tA __________ checkpoint is a checkpoint where transactions are allowed to perform updates even while buffer blocks are being written out.",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tTemporary",
            "b)\tFuzzy",
            "c)\tPermanent",
            "d)\tRecovery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using checkpoints reduces overhead because the search process is time consuming and searching for transactions does not take place if we use checkpoints. "
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "10.\tIf the database modifications occur while the transaction is still active, the transaction is said to use the __________ modification technique",
        "Options": [
            "a)\tDeferred",
            "b)\tImmediate",
            "c)\tMore than one of the mentioned",
            "d)\tNone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A fuzzy checkpoint is a checkpoint where transactions are allowed to perform updates even while buffer blocks are being written out. "
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Options": [
            "create table branch",
            "   (branch_name \tvarchar(15)\tnot null unique,",
            "    branch_city \tvarchar(15)\tnot null,",
            "    assets \t\tnumber\t\tnot null,",
            "    primary key(branch_name));"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: create table account\n   (account_number \tvarchar(15)\tnot null unique,\n    branch_name\t\tvarchar(15)\tnot null,\n    balance \t\tnumber\t\tnot null,\n    primary key(account_number));\n\n\n\tcreate table branch\n   (branch_name \tvarchar(15)\tnot null unique,\n    branch_city \tvarchar(15)\tnot null,\n    assets \t\tnumber\t\tnot null,\n    primary key(branch_name));\ncreate table customer\n   (customer_name \tvarchar(15)\tnot null unique,\n    customer_street \tvarchar(12)\tnot null,\n    customer_city \tvarchar(15)\tnot null,\n    primary key(customer_name));\n\n\n\t\n\n        create table loan\n   (loan_number \tvarchar(15)\tnot null unique,\n    branch_name\t\tvarchar(15)\tnot null,\n    amount \t\tnumber\t\tnot null,\n    primary key(loan_number));\ncreate table depositor\n   (customer_name \tvarchar(15)\tnot null,\n    account_number \tvarchar(15)\tnot null,\n    primary key(customer_name, account_number),\n    foreign key(account_number) references account(account_number),\n    foreign key(customer_name) references customer(customer_name));\n\n\n        create table borrower\n   (customer_name \tvarchar(15)\tnot null,\n    loan_number \tvarchar(15)\tnot null,\n    primary key(customer_name, loan_number),\n    foreign key(customer_name) references customer(customer_name),\n    foreign key(loan_number) references loan(loan_number)); "
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "create table customer",
            "   (customer_name \tvarchar(15)\tnot null unique,",
            "    customer_street \tvarchar(12)\tnot null,",
            "    customer_city \tvarchar(15)\tnot null,",
            "    primary key(customer_name));"
        ]
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "create table loan",
            "   (loan_number \tvarchar(15)\tnot null unique,",
            "    branch_name\t\tvarchar(15)\tnot null,",
            "    amount \t\tnumber\t\tnot null,",
            "    primary key(loan_number));"
        ]
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "create table depositor",
        "Options": [
            "   (customer_name \tvarchar(15)\tnot null,",
            "    account_number \tvarchar(15)\tnot null,",
            "    primary key(customer_name, account_number),",
            "    foreign key(account_number) references account(account_number),",
            "    foreign key(customer_name) references customer(customer_name));"
        ]
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "create table borrower",
        "Options": [
            "   (customer_name \tvarchar(15)\tnot null,",
            "    loan_number \tvarchar(15)\tnot null,",
            "    primary key(customer_name, loan_number),",
            "    foreign key(customer_name) references customer(customer_name),",
            "    foreign key(loan_number) references loan(loan_number));"
        ]
    }
]